<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Londons gate to the Lords Table. Where the eldership doth sit doing their office aright, in discovering and shutting out the ignorant, prophane, and meere civill honest man : in suspending the suspected formall, legall, and antinomisticall professor, and in drawing in the weakest humble beleeving soule. In a dialogue betweene a minister of the Gospell. Alexander an ignorant prophane man. Simon a proud professor. And Matthias an humble penitent. Imprimatur Edmund Calamy.</title>
            <author>Fisher, Edward, fl. 1627-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 152 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1213_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210120</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868946</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85329)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 251:E1213[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Londons gate to the Lords Table. Where the eldership doth sit doing their office aright, in discovering and shutting out the ignorant, prophane, and meere civill honest man : in suspending the suspected formall, legall, and antinomisticall professor, and in drawing in the weakest humble beleeving soule. In a dialogue betweene a minister of the Gospell. Alexander an ignorant prophane man. Simon a proud professor. And Matthias an humble penitent. Imprimatur Edmund Calamy.</title>
                  <author>Fisher, Edward, fl. 1627-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 274 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Wright at the Kings Head in the old Bayley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647. [i.e. 1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication and preface signed: E.F., i.e. Edward Fisher.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb 28"; the 7 in the imprint date has been altered to "8".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Doctrine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's supper --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170659:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDONS GATE</hi> TO The Lords Table.</p>
            <p>Where the Elderſhip doth ſit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their office aright, in diſcovering and ſhutting out the ignorant, prophane, and meere civill honeſt man: In ſuſpending the ſuſpected formall, legall, and Antinomiſticall Profeſſor, and in drawing in the weakeſt humble beleeving ſoule.</p>
            <p>In a Dialogue betweene</p>
            <list>
               <item>A Miniſter of the Goſpell.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> an ignorant prophane man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Simon</hi> a proud Profeſſor.</item>
               <item>And <hi>Matthias</hi> an humble penitent.</item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mal. 3. 18.</bibl> Then ſhall ye returne and diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the righteous and the wicked, between him that ſerveth God, and him that ſerveth him not.</q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Edmund Calamy.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>London printed for <hi>Iohn Wright</hi> at the Kings Head in the old Bayley. 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170659:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170659:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable HENRY ROLLE, one of his Majeſties Juſtices of Pleas, before himſelfe to be holden.</head>
            <head type="sub">And to the vertuous Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman MARGARET ROLLE his loving Wife, grace and peace be multiplied.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST honoured friends; cuſtom hath made the Dedication of Books almoſt as common as printing of them, and wiſdome directs there to dedicate where we owe
<pb facs="tcp:170659:3"/> moſt reſpect, and doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they will be beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. I therefore owing my ſervice to you both for ſome favours recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and preſuming upon your favourable accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, have made bold to prefixe your names to this enſuing Dialogue, which I hope holds forth a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle light to that way of Church-Diſcipline which you, Honoured Sir, have beene pleaſed much to countenance, by conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending ſo farre below yourſelf (as ſome of your ranke would have eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it) in accepting of the Office of a Ruling-El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when you were cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
<pb facs="tcp:170659:3"/> in that Congregation whereof you have beene pleaſed to admit mee a member.</p>
            <p>I have endeavoured to diſcover the exactneſſe of the Presbyteriall way in the caſe of examination of Communicants, and how circumſpect you are who you doe admit, that ſo our diſcenting brethren, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how neere you come to the golden rule, may bee moved thereby to come in amongſt us, that we may <hi>be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde and in the ſame judgement, and ſo knit together in love according to Gods owne minde, 1 Cor. 1. 10. Col.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170659:4"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:170659:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:170659:5"/> For as a gracious ſpirit<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sibs</hi> bruſed reed, p. 220.</note> once breathed out, there can hardly be a diſcovery of any difference in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion without ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrangement of affection, ſo far as men are not of one minde they will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be of one heart, except where grace and the peace of God beare great rule in the heart.</p>
            <p>Wherefore if my work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip in the handling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f this ſubject, were as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>od as my aimes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ions are, I might boldly ſay, It were no diſparagement to your names to afford it your patronage; yet will I not diſparage it, for that may
<pb facs="tcp:170659:5"/> be thought to be a ſecret begging of commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; onely I ſay, I having thus farre preſumed, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you both to connive at my boldneſſe, and vouchſafe to favour theſe mine endeavours, that ſo by your acceptance they may be commended unto others, and ſo ſhall you further oblige me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours much engaged, E. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170659:6"/>
            <head>To the well-affected READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I did conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore by the command of Authority all ſorts of people that were come to ripeneſſe of yeares, and were endued with underſtanding, were not only admitted, but alſo compelled by Law to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper at leaſt once a yeare.</p>
            <p>And that now contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, Authority were ſo far from compelling in that kinde, that by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand none were to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:170659:6"/> thereunto, but onely ſuch as upon examination were found fit to partake thereof.</p>
            <p>I began to conſider more then formerly I had done of the reaſon why all ſorts of people might not as well be admitted to that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as they were to the hearing of the Ward prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: And when I had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſidered of it, I found (as I conceived) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon why none but true Beleevers were to bee admitted thereunto, and that therefore the power given to the Elderſhip for that purpoſe, was very law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and needfull to be put in execution with maturity
<pb facs="tcp:170659:7"/> of judgement, it being a matter of very ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, if they ſhould either open the gate to any unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, or ſhut it againſt any true beleever; and a very hard matter ſo to diſcerne of the ſtate and condition of every one that commeth before them, as never to doe the one nor the other.</p>
            <p>In which reſpect I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they ſtood in great need not only of the prayers, but alſo of all other helps that any of Gods people could afford them, I therefore as a member of the body (though but a weake one) was willing to afford my beſt aſſiſtance towards the carrying on of ſuch a great
<pb facs="tcp:170659:7"/> worke, and not knowing which way to doe it better, then by compoſing my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations touching that point into a plaine and familiar Dialogue; I did thereupon adventure to put forth a ſmall Tract, intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>A Touchſtone for a Communicant,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon better conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, conceiving it came far ſhort of diſcovering all that was needfull to bee knowne touching theſe points, I (in hope that my ſecond thoughts would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed my firſt) was moved to ſet pen to paper once again. And the Lord having (as I hope I may truly ſay) ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled me to doe more and
<pb facs="tcp:170659:8"/> better, I have againe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to put it forth to the worlds view, though I am confident I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by expoſed my ſelfe to the worlds cenſure.</p>
            <p>For indeed I doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that if any man doe but know my weakneſſe (and my want of thoſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane helps, which many others doe enjoy) ſo well as my ſelfe doe know them, if they conſult with fleſh and blood, they ſhall ſee juſt cauſe to ſay with <hi>Nathani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, Joh. 1. 46. Can there any good thing come out of Nazareth;</hi> yea, and to ſay unto me as <hi>Eliab</hi> ſaid unto <hi>David, I know the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17. 28.</note> 
               <hi>pride and the naughtineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:170659:8"/> of thy heart;</hi> theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are not fit for thee to meddle withall, they rather belong to ſome of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Aſſembly. But if they will bee pleaſed to conſult with the Oracles of God, they ſhall ſee that in the building of <hi>SOLOMONS</hi> Temple there was roome as well for burden-bearers as for other more curious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers, <hi>1 King. 5. 15.</hi> yea, and they ſhall ſee that at the firſt making of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle,<note place="margin">Exo. 25. 5.</note> not onely the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of blue ſilke, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſcarlet, but even the poorer ſort, which brought Goats haire and Rams skins were accepted; yea, and they ſhall finde that
<pb facs="tcp:170659:9"/> the Lord made <hi>Balaams</hi> aſſe<note place="margin">Num. 22. 28.</note> to utter his truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray thee doe not cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure either me or the work, before thou haſt thorowly peruſed it; and whatſoever wants, weakneſſes, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections thou findeſt in it, I pray thee cover them with the mantle of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, aſſuring thy ſelfe that I would have done better if I could: And if thou finde any good in it, I pray thee take occaſion from the weakneſſe and unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Author, to ſee God the more clearly, and to give him the more glory, whoſe <hi>ſtrength is made</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 9.</note> perfect through weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170659:9"/>
            <p>And though thou be a diſcenting brother from that Church-way which the Title Page hath told thee it holds forth; yet let not that hinder thee from peruſing of it, for I doe aſſure thee there is more matter in it concerning Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine then there is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Church Diſcipline; ſo that although it may not pleaſe thee the one way, yet (if thou be a Chriſtian) it may pleaſe thee the other way.</p>
            <p>But if thou haſt ſuch a proud cenſorious heart, as doth either hinder thee from reading it, or elſe from receiving any benefit by it, yet if it bring any little
<pb facs="tcp:170659:10"/> increaſe either of ſound knowledge or ſweet feeling in the myſteries of Chriſt to any of the Iſrael of God that is of an humble ſpirit, as bleſſed be God (I have beene informed) my <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of moderne Divinity</hi> hath done to many; I have my reward, and ſhall deſire to magnifie the name of the Lord for making uſe of ſuch a weake inſtrument as I am.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:170659:10"/>
            <head>A Table of the principall matters contained in this Dialogue.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THere is an ignorance and ſinfulneſſe in part, and an ignorance and ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in whole. 6</item>
               <item>The tryall of one that is wholly ignorant. 8</item>
               <item>The tryall of a man that is wholy ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>A kind of ſtriving againſt ſinne in a man that is wholly ſinfull. 18</item>
               <item>The different ſtriving that is in a man who is wholly ſinfull, and a man that is in part ſinfull. 21</item>
               <item>There is no true faith in a man wholly ignorant and wholly ſinfull. 25</item>
               <item>One that hath not true faith; ought not to partake of the Sacrament of the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. 26</item>
               <item>The danger of receiving the ſacrament without faith. 33</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170659:11"/>
               <item>The exhortation of the a Apoſtle, 1 Cor. 11 28. <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe</hi> doth not exclude his examination by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. 47</item>
               <item>Not eaſily determined whether a man be fit to partake of the ſacrament or no. 49</item>
               <item>Tis lawfull and needfull for a man before he receive the ſacrament to goe to bee exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before the Elderſhip. 50</item>
               <item>Tis lawfull and needfull for the Elders to ioyne with the Miniſter in the buſineſſe of examination. 54</item>
               <item>Deſcription of the Elderſhips examining all that come before them. 68. 149</item>
               <item>Tis not meet for every member of the Church to have an equall authority with the Elderſhip. 58</item>
               <item>A man of great knowledge and righteous converſation, may be unfit to be admitted to the ſacrament. 61</item>
               <item>The life of civility deſcribed. 77</item>
               <item>The life of rationall and religious for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality deſcribed. 82</item>
               <item>God juſtifieth the ungodly. 88</item>
               <item>God maketh a man juſt before he do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him juſt. 89</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170659:11"/>
               <item>How God maketh a man juſt. 91</item>
               <item>Why or in what ſence a man is ſaid to be juſtified by faith. ibid.</item>
               <item>The act of God in pronouncing a man juſt, what it is. 95</item>
               <item>Where righteouſneſſe of justification is imputed, righteouſneſſe of ſanctification is infuſed. 97</item>
               <item>How the righteouſneſſe of juſtification and the righteouſneſſe of ſanctification doe differ. 99</item>
               <item>Two ſorts of profeſſors doe confound this twofold righteouſneſſe. 103</item>
               <item>There is both a faith and a godlineſſe of a mans owne aquiring 121</item>
               <item>If a man hath not both the righteouſneſſe of juſtification and the righteouſneſſe of ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, he hath neither of them. 122</item>
               <item>How a man may know that he hath them both. 124</item>
               <item>A man may in word and judgement re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his rwne righteouſneſſe in the caſe of juſtification, and yet not do ſo in heart and conſcience. 133</item>
               <item>Signes of a mans putting confidence in his owne righteouſneſſe. 137</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170659:12"/>
               <item>No cauſe why any man ſhould either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to go, or continue in that way which for diſtinctions ſake is called the independent way. 164</item>
               <item>No perfect platforme of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be found in the new Teſtament, ſaid a godly Miniſter, in the pulpit. 166</item>
               <item>A gracious anſwer lately given by old Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> to one that came to aske him a circumſtantiall queſtion. 170</item>
               <item>The heginning of conference with <hi>Mathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> an humble penitent. 171</item>
               <item>How he was firſt moved to minde the beſt things. 178</item>
               <item>The Lord doth firſt give faith to beleeve the pardon of ſinne before he give power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne. 181</item>
               <item>The Lord pardoneth ſinne abſolutely and not conditionally. 184</item>
               <item>To beleeve the pardon of ſinne, is the way to get power againſt ſinne. 185</item>
               <item>The Lord doth firſt pardon ſinne, and then he ſubdues it. 189</item>
               <item>A true feare of Gods diſpleaſure, works a ſeparation betwixt the heart and ſinne. 192</item>
               <item>A deſire to beleeve is faith indeed. 196</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170659:12"/>
               <item>The difference betwixt naturall deſires and ſupernaturall. 199</item>
               <item>A true evidence of a ſound minde. 205</item>
               <item>How to underſtand theſe words, Worthy, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy. 214</item>
               <item>Chriſt neither accepts any for greatneſſe of parts, nor refuſeth any for weakneſſe of parts. 227</item>
               <item>Though there can be no faith where there is no knowledge, yet may there be a great meaſure of knowledge where there is no faith. 129</item>
               <item>It is the kinde of faith that fits a man to the Sacrament, and not the meaſure. 231</item>
               <item>It is not a ſight and ſenſe of knowledge, nor faith, nor repentance, nor love, nor obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, that makes a man worthy to come to the Sacrament, but rather an hungring and thirſting appetite after Chriſt, ariſing from a ſight and ſenſe of the want of ſuch things. 235</item>
               <item>The wedding garment what it is. 236</item>
               <item>Why the Lords ſupper was inſtituted and ordained. 240</item>
               <item>What meditations we ought to have at the Lords Table. 244</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:170659:13"/>
               <item>The reaſon why we are to receive the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords ſupper often, though baptized but once. 254</item>
               <item>Much good gotten by the right receiving of the Lordt ſupper. 261</item>
               <item>He that is unfit to receive the ſacrament ſinneth whether he receive it or not. ibid.</item>
               <item>What be the hinderances that keepe many from the ſacrament. 263</item>
               <item>How to become poore in ſpirit. 267</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170659:13"/>
            <head>LONDONS Gate TO The Lords Table.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Interlocutors</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>A <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Goſpell.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alexander,</hi> an ignorant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane man.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simon,</hi> a proud Profeſſor.</item>
                     <item>And <hi>Matthias,</hi> a weak, yet true Beleever.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div n="1-51" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Simon,</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, when I part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with you the other day, I did not think to have come unto you ſo ſoon againe: but indeed having better conſidered
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170659:14"/> of it, I ſee I was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what deceived in our neighbour <hi>Zacheus,</hi> for the truth is, he anſwered you better then I had thought hee could have done. But yet here is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other neighbor of ours, in whom I am ſure I am not deceived, for all that have any acquaintance with him, and have any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Religion, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that hee is a very ſimple ignorant man, and a bad liver; and yet he ſaith, That he hopes the Lord would be mercifull unto him and forgive him his ſinnes, if hee ſhould come to the Sacrament. And he telling me that he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170659:14"/> was going to your houſe to ſpeake with you about it, I was willing to come along with him, to ſee if you would judge him alſo fit to partake of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ordinance, and our neighbour <hi>Matthias</hi> hath thought good to come along with us to heare our diſcourſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>You be all of you very welcome to me, and I ſhall be very willing to doe any good I can to any of you: And truly neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Simon</hi> I was ſorry you went away the other day in ſuch a diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed manner; for I ſhould have beene glad if you had tarried longer, that wee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170659:15"/> might have had further conference together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I thanke you, it may be we may have further conference toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about thoſe things before we part; but firſt of all I pray you hearken to our neighbour <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> for he hath ſomewhat to ſay unto you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Come neer neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Alexander,</hi> and tell me what you have to ſay unto me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that as my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Simon</hi> hath ſaid, I am a very ignorant man, and am now and then ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to drinke more then I ſhould doe, and to ſweare
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170659:15"/> now and then an Oath when I am vexed, but I am ſory for it afterwards. Now Sir, I doe deſire to know the reaſon why I for all this may not be admitted unto the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an ignorant and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, muſt needs be an unbeleeving man, and the Sacrament of the Lords Supper was not inſtituted and ordained for any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleever.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, though I be (as I have confeſſed) an ignorant and ſinfull man, yet I hope I am a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving man for all that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170659:16"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Sir, I pray you is every ignorant and ſinfull man an unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No not ſo neither, for there is a twofold Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and a twofold ſinfulneſſe; that is to ſay, there is an ignorance and ſinfulneſſe in part, and an ignorance and ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in whole; now a man may be ignorant in part, and yet have true faith in Chriſt; for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith concerning himſelfe, and other true beleevers, <hi>We know but in part, 1 Cor.</hi> 13. 9. yea, and a man may be alſo ſinfull
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170659:16"/> in part, and yet be a true beleever, witneſſe the ſame Apoſtle, when hee ſaith, <hi>Rom. 7. 23. I finde a law in my members rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt the law of my minde, and bringing mee into captivity to the law of ſinne.</hi> But if a man bee wholly ignorant of Jeſus Chriſt, and of himſelfe, and of the Sacrament, as for ought I yet perceive you are, and wholly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as by your own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion it appears you are, then it is impoſſible hee ſhould have true faith in Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, I hope I am not wholly ignorant of Jeſus Chriſt, nor of my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170659:17"/> ſelfe, nor of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, becauſe you ſay ſo, I pray you give me leave to aske you two or three queſtions; and firſt of all I pray you tell mee what is Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, he is Gods onely Sonne, who was conceived by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But the Scripture ſaith, That GOD hath more ſonnes then one, as it is written, <hi>Galat. 3. 26. For ye are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> why doe you then ſay, That Chriſt is Gods onely Sonne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170659:17"/>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I ſay ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo ſet downe in the Apoſtles Creed, which I am ſure I ſay many a time and often; and if it be not true, me thinks the Apoſtles of Chriſt ſhould not have ſo ſet it downe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is the holy Ghoſt which you ſay Chriſt was conceived by?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, the Holy Ghoſt I think is that good Spirit whereby we are guided and ruled when we live and walke according to Gods will and Commandments.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And why was Chriſt conceived by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Beleeve me Sir,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170659:18"/> that is too hard a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for me to anſwer, and it would trouble a man that hath much more knowledge then I to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer aright.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And why do you ſay that Chriſt was borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I ſay ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſo ſaid in my Creed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But why was it meet that he ſhould bee borne of a Virgin, rather then of another woman?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly Sir, I know no other reaſon, then that I am perſwaded it was the will of God it ſhould be ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170659:18"/> you are a ſinner; therefore I pray you tell me how you came to be a ſinner?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why by yeelding to the Devils tentations and mine own wicked and corrupt heart, as other ſinners do I thinke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But was you born a ſinner?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſinne did my mother conceive me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And was you a ſinner when you were firſt created in <hi>Adam?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea ſurely, or elſe how could I be borne a ſinner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what doe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170659:19"/> you beleeve that Chriſt hath done for you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I do verily beleeve that he died for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But what warrant have you to beleeve that Chriſt died for you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Chriſt died for ſinners, and I am a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and therefore I doe beleeve that he died for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And do you think that Chriſt died for all men?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, if he died for ſinners, I thinke he muſt needs die for all men, for wee are all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you then beleeve
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170659:19"/> that all men ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, I am not ſo ſimple to think that all men ſhall be ſaved, for as I doe beleeve there is a Heaven for ſome, ſo do I beleeve there is a Hell for others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why do you then thinke that Chriſt died in vaine for them that are not ſaved?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſurely I dare not think ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But if he died to ſave them, and they bee not ſaved, muſt it not needs follow, that he died for them in vaine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly Sir I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how to anſwer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170659:20"/> that, it is too hard a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and therefore I pray you aſke mee no more ſuch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then, I pray you tell me what is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why a Sacrament is the Lords Supper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And why do you deſire to come to the Lords Supper?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>That I might there worſhip and ſerve the Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well neighbour <hi>Alexander,</hi> I might aſke you many other queſtions touching theſe points, but your Anſwers to theſe I have already aſked you, are ſufficient to prove that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170659:20"/> you are wholly ignorant, of Chriſt, of your ſelfe, and of the Sacrament, for though ſome of your an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers be true, yet as wee uſe to ſay, As good never a whit, as never the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, for ought I ſee, thoſe that have moſt knowledge in Religion, and can talke beſt of it, are as bad in their lives as they that are moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and therefore if I have but a good heart and a good minde, as I doubt not but I have, I hope I ſhall doe as well at the laſt as if I could talke and prate more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I but whatſoever
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170659:21"/> you thinke of your ſelfe, and whatever your hopes are, the Lord tells you, <hi>Prov. 19. 2. That without knowledge the heart or minde is not good;</hi> and although it be poſſible that a man of great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge may have an evill heart of unbeleefe, and ſo periſh, yet it is without all queſtion, that hee who hath no knowledge hath an evil heart of unbeleefe, and therefore ſhall periſh, as it is written, <hi>Hoſ. 3. 6. My people periſh for want of knowledge.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>And Sir, do you alſo thinke that I am wholly ſinfull?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed do I,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170659:21"/> for an ignorant heart is alwayes a ſinfull heart, and a man without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is alwayes a man without grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, when you ſay I am wholly ſinfull, I pray you tell me what you meane, for I do not well underſtand you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I meane you are wholly given over to ſinne, you commit ſinne with greedineſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtrife in your will and affections againſt it; you love ſinne, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the committing of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay now Sir, I ſee you are deceived in me, for I thanke God I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170659:22"/> doe ſtrive againſt my ſins, and would faine leave off my ſinfull courſes, and as the ſaying is, My Spirit is willing, but my Fleſh is weake; The Lord bee mercifull unto mee, and forgive me all my ſinnes, as I hope he will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But what is your meaning, when you ſay, You doe ſtrive againſt your ſinnes, and would faine leave them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, That when I am overcome by drinking too much, and do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon fall to curſing and ſwearing, quarrelling, and ſome other ſinnes; when I come to my ſelfe againe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170659:22"/> and have conſidered what I have ſaid and done, I am much vexed at my ſelfe, and wiſh from my heart that I had never done ſo; yea, and I have many a time reſolved ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to do the like againe; and yet by occaſion of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the company of ſome men, with whom I have ſome dealing, who are too ſubject to that vice (though otherwiſe very honeſt faire conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned men) and alſo by reaſon of mine own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination to thoſe ſinnes, I am now and then overcome, and ſo commit the like ſinnes againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what hath
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170659:23"/> beene the reaſon of this your ſtriving againſt your ſinnes, as you call it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, it hath been becauſe I have conſidered that in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I have miſ-ſpent my time and my money, and have diſgraced my ſelfe, and endangered the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mine owne ſoule, if the Lord were not the more mercifull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely it appears to me that all this ſtriving hath beene onely betwixt your Judgement and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, or betwixt your Conſcience &amp; your Luſts; You doe in your Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conceive theſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to be evill, becauſe of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170659:23"/> the evill effects that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, and therefore your conſcience tells you that you do evil in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, and you thinke it were good for you to leave them becauſe of the puniſhment that follows or is like to follow upon the committing of them; but your Affections and Luſts do like and approve of them, and therefore doe prevaile with you to act and commit them, and in the committing of them you take great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; ſo that I ſay, this your ſtriving againſt ſinne is nothing but Conſcience and Luſts by the ears to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which ſtriving <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170659:24"/> Balaam,</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> had within them, and ſo may the vileſt Reprobate in the world have: But all this while there is no ſtrife in you betwixt will and will, nor betwixt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Affection, as there is in every true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever; for he having the Spirit of Chriſt within him is a regenerate man, and in part renewed, and therefore the ſtrife that is in him is betwixt the Fleſh and the Spirit, betwixt the regenerate part and the unregenerate part, and it is againſt ſinne as it is ſinne, and hated and loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed by him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſſure your ſelfe that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170659:24"/> notwithſtanding all your ſtriving, you are wholly ſinfull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſtay a little, I pray Sir, this your ſpeech ſeemeth to imply, as though a true Beleever might commit the like groſſe ſinnes that he doth, and that there were no other difference betwixt him and a true Beleever in the point of ſinning, but onely this different ſtriving.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But aſſure your ſelfe neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> that my meaning is not ſo, for I doe fully agree with that worthy man of God, who ſaith, That a true Repentant, and that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170659:25"/> is a true Beleever, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakes all ſinne in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all groſſe ſinne in action; and therefore I pray you neighbour <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> conſider of it, for this doth more fully prove that you are wholly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as well as wholly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, though I be wholly ignorant and wholly ſinfull, as you ſay, yet would I faine know the reaſon why I may not have true faith in Chriſt for all that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The reaſon why there can be no true faith in Chriſt when a man is wholly ignorant of him, is becauſe it is the nature
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170659:25"/> of faith to beleeve that which it knoweth; ſo that whereſoever there is no true knowledge of Chriſt there can be no true faith in Chriſt; and therefore<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reynolds</hi> on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, p. 138.</note> Chriſt himſelfe makes the knowledge of him all one with beleefe in him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. 3.</p>
                  <p>And the reaſon why there can be no true faith in Chriſt when a man is wholly ſinfull is, becauſe holineſſe of life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is an unſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble companion and fruit of faith; for <hi>faith purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the heart,</hi> Acts 15. 9. and <hi>faith worketh by love,</hi> Gal. 5. 6.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170659:26"/> I have no true faith in Chriſt, and ſo be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleever, as you ſay; Yet why was not the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per inſtituted and ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for unbeleevers as well as for beleevers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, being not the Sacrament of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, but of ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and nouriſhment, Chriſt did not inſtitute and ordaine it for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generating or converting of any man, nor for the breeding of grace in him, but for the ſtrengthning of the regenerate man that is borne againe, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170659:26"/> for the nouriſhment of grace already bred and begun in him, ſo that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is childrens bread, even the bread of Gods children, that are <hi>borne againe, not of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 23</note> 
                     <hi>ſeed but of incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, by the word of God which liveth and abideth for ever;</hi> and therefore it is not to bee given unto dogs; yea, it is ſpirituall food, ordained for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually living men; and therefore it is not to bee put into the mouthes of ſpiritually dead men, but into the ſoules of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally living men; and a man is made a ſonne of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170659:27"/> God onely by faith in Chriſt, as it is written, Joh. 1. 12. <hi>To as many as received him, to them gave he power to become the ſons of God, even to them that beleeve on his Name.</hi> And ſo <hi>Gal. 3. 16. Ye are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> yea, &amp; it is faith that quickens a man and maks him ſpiritually alive according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal. 2. 20. I live by the faith of the Son of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is the Seale of a Covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. and Covenants eſſentially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude conditions, and the condition on our part is Faith, ſo that where there
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170659:27"/> is no Faith there is no Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and where there is no Covenant there is no Seale, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently no Sacrament; ſo that you being an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleever, you are an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted un-regenerate man, no childe of God, no ſpiritually living man, neither are you under the Covenant of Grace; and therefore aſſure your ſelfe the ſacrament of the Lords Supper was not inſtituted and ordained for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, it ſeems that you do not intend to admit me to bee a parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely neighbour
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170659:28"/> 
                     <hi>Alexander,</hi> you not having true faith in Chriſt, you cannot bee a partaker thereof, though we ſhould admit you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>This is ſtrange to me Sir, cannot I come to Church and receive the Bread and Wine, and eat it, and drinke it, if you give it me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea I do confeſſe, though you have no faith yet you may partake of the Bread and Wine; but you are not to come to the Sacrament to partake of the Bread and Wine, but to be made a partaker of CHRISTS Body and Blood, under the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Bread and Wine,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170659:28"/> but this you cannot doe without Faith, for Faith is the hand with which Chriſt is received as you may ſee, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. 12. yea, and it is the mouth by which we feed on him, as you may ſee, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 53. wherefore I beſeech you bee not ſo ſimple as to thinke and imagine that you are to come to the Sacrament for a morſell of finer Bread, or for a draught of ſweet Wine; nor that if you receive the outward Elements in a reverend manner, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have your ſelfe decent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly during that action, and demeane your ſelfe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly for that day, that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170659:29"/> then you have received the Sacrament in honour of Chriſt, and done a right acceptable ſervice to God. But know and conſider, That the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Banquet, where we are to feaſt our ſoules with the Body and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt crucified for us; and this you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do for want of Faith: and therefore, if you ſhould come and partake of the outward Elements, yet would it be no benefit to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, doe you thinke it would bee any hurt to me, if I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170659:29"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, I know it would be great hurt to you for by reaſon of your Ignorance and want of Faith in Chriſt; you are neither able to <hi>examine your ſelfe</hi> before you come there, nor <hi>to diſcerne the Lords Body</hi> when you are there, and ſo ſhould you receive the Sacrament <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily;</hi> and ſo not only be <hi>guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord, but alſo eat and drinke damnation to your ſelfe,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tells you, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 27. 28, 29.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, theſe things are ſomewhat ſtrange to me, and therefore I pray you give me leave to aſk
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170659:30"/> you a few queſtions about them, and firſt of all tell me what I ought to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine my ſelfe of, becauſe you ſay I am not able to doe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why you ought to examine your ſelfe<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5</note> whether you bee in the Faith, whether Chriſt be in you yea or no, whether you be dead to ſinne or alive to righteouſneſſe, what graces you have and what you want, what cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions you have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and what do over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you, what religious actions you perform, and how you performe them; in briefe, to examine your ſelfe, is to take a true ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170659:30"/> of the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of your ſoule, by comparing it with the Scriptures. Now you are ignorant both of the ſtate and condition of your ſoule, and alſo of the Scriptures, and therefore I ſay it is impoſſible that you ſhould be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine your ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, and what is it to diſcerne the Lords Body?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>To diſcerne the LORDS Bodie, is to put a right difference betweene the outward Elements in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and common<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pemble</hi> on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, p. 59.</note> Bread and Wine, which difference is not at all in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170659:31"/> ſubſtance but in the uſe, the one being prophane the other ſacred, being ſet a part to ſignifie unto us the benefits of Chriſts death and paſſion; or the diſcerning of the Lords Body ſtands in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, underſtanding and<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dike</hi> on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. p. 90.</note> judgement of the nature, uſe, and neceſſitie of the Sacrament; but you have manifeſted by that which you ſaid ere while, That you put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Bread and Wine at the Lords Table and common bread and wine, but would uſe them as you doe your ordinarie food, without any regard of the ſpirituall uſe of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170659:31"/> them, and therefore you are not able to diſcerne the Lords Body at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, it would be a ſtrange thing if I by receiving the Sacrament ſhould become guilty of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; I pray you Sir ſhew me the reaſon of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if you ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament, you would doe even ſo as the ſhedders of Chriſts Blood did, for looke as they that crucified and pierced Chriſt, poured not forth his Blood that they might<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dike</hi> on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments p. 56.</note> drinke it, but onely that they might poure it forth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170659:32"/> and ſhed it, ſo you by your receiving the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without profit or benefit to your ſoule, would raſhly and in vaine ſhed the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Or to be guiltie of the Body and Blood of Chriſt<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Reynolds</hi> on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, p. 180.</note> is to offer ſome notable contempt unto the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt, to finne againſt the price of our Redemption, and to vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and ſet at naught the precious Blood of the new Covenant, as if it were a common and prophane thing, when men out of ignorant, ſenſuall, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, preſumptuous for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malizing, inconſiderate and prophane affections
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170659:32"/> approach unto Chriſts Table to communicate of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>And do you think that I ſhould eat and drink damnation to my ſelfe, if I ſhould receive the Bread and Wine at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I think you would commit ſuch a ſinne in prophaning the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as deſerves both eternall and temporall Judgement, for though this Table of the Lord be a Feaſt of choiceſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for refreſhing of the<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pemble</hi> on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, p. 66.</note> ſoule, when men come rightly prepared thereto, yet doth it become the bane and deſtruction of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170659:33"/> ſoules, when men preſent themſelves thereat with unbeleeving impenitent and unholy hearts, as you would doe if you ſhould come there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, it ſeems you doe abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that I am unfit to be admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely neighbour <hi>Alexander,</hi> you being wholly ignorant &amp; whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinfull, unbeleeving, unregenerate, unconvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, no Sonne of God, no ſpiritually living man, and having neither hand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt, nor mouth to feed on Chriſt, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170659:33"/> able to examine your ſelfe, nor to diſcerne the Lords Bodie, and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receiver, and ſo liable to become guilty of the Bodie and Blood of Chriſt, and to eat and drink your own damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I think it muſt needs follow that you are unfit to be admitted to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the LORDS Supper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, if the caſe ſtand thus with me, then ſurely I have no cauſe to be ſorry (as ſome are) but rather glad that the Parliament have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch a courſe, that you Miniſters and Elders in every Pariſh ſhall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170659:34"/> every one before he be admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for if it had not beene for that, and if all might have come to the Sacrament that would, as it was in the Biſhops dayes, then had I two or three times at the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Scrament of late, though, as it ſeems, it had been to the hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſalvation of my ſoule: But Sir, what would you adviſe mee to do, in regard I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore received it divers times?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſurely, I would adviſe you to goe unto the Lord by often and fervent prayer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170659:34"/> him to pardon and forgive you that, and all your other ſins, for his Sonne Jeſus Chriſts ſake, and to give you faith to beleeve the pardon and forgiveneſſe of them, and to give you repentance for them, and ſo to make you a new creature: And I would alſo adviſe you to become a diligent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the Word of God, and read it often, that ſo you may come to know your ſelf and Jeſus Chriſt, with the nature, uſe, and neceſſity of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and by theſe and other ſuch meanes it may pleaſe the Lord to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert your ſoule, and to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170659:35"/> make you fit to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lords Table, and then we ſhall willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receive you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, it ſeems I may be permitted to heare the Word of God preached?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, I do not only permit you, but alſo exhort you thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for that is the ſpeciall meanes which God hath ordained for the convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſoules, and for the breeding of grace in the heart of his Elect, and therefore I ſay I doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you, yea, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you as you tender the good of your ſoule, have a ſpeciall care of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170659:35"/> that, and when you finde that the Lord hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wrought upon your heart, then come before me and the Elders to be examined, and in the meane time I will pray for you, and ſo for this time I have done with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alex.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then Sir, I will take my leave of you, and I thanke you for the paines you have taken with me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Fare you well neighbour <hi>Alexander,</hi> and I beſeech the Lord to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of your ſinnes, and convert you to the faith of Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, now
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170659:36"/> you have pleaſed mee wondrous well, for now I ſee you will not admit of every ignorant and prophane fellow to come to the Sacrament, and truly now I could almoſt finde in my heart to come in amongſt you and joyne my ſelfe with you, were it not for this buſineſſe of Examination, but that I cannot approve of; and to tell you the truth, ſince I was here with you the other day, I met with a friend of mine, unto whom I related your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Zacheus,</hi> and he ſaid, That there was no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in Scripture, either
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170659:36"/> for Miniſter or Elders to examine any one before they come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; indeed, ſaid hee, the Apoſtle exhorts a man to examine himſelfe before he come, but he doth not exhort any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to examine him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any place of Scripture that warrants it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But whoſoever your friend was, hee is much deceived, for the Apoſtle in exhorting a man to examine himſelf, doth not exclude his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination by another, but rather includes it; and though there be no place of Scripture that doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly require one man to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170659:37"/> examine another before he come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet may it bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered from Scripture by neceſſary conſequence, for I thinke no man will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that command of the Lord, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 6. 7. to Parents to Catechiſe their children and ſervants, and to take an account of their Faith; and ſurely if Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 15</note> bee ſpirituall Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as indeed they are, then by the like reaſon they are warranted to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine their people, and to take an account of their Faith. And ſurely I doe conceive that the practice of thoſe Chriſtians is both warrantable and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170659:37"/> who in any caſe of conſcience which is not eaſily determined, doe repaire to ſome god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſter for his advice and counſell therein, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that <hi>the Lord</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 50. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>hath given unto them the tongue of the learned, that they ſhould know how to ſpeake a word in ſeaſon.</hi> And conſidering alſo that the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Prieſts lips ſhould keep</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mal. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>knowledge, and men ſhould ſeeke the Law of God at his mouth;</hi> and this caſe of conſcience, to wit, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man be fit to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Sacrament yea or no, I doe conceive is not very eaſily deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170659:38"/> and therefore as the Eunuch ſaid unto <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 8. 36.</note> 
                     <hi>See, here is water, what doth hinder me to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized?</hi> So I do conceive that it is meet for every man and woman, before they receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to goe to ſome godly Miniſter, or rather now before the Elderſhip, and ſay, I underſtand that ſuch a day the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, what doth hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der me to partake there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that it is meet for them to anſwer with <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip, If thou beleeveſt with all thine heart, thou maieſt;</hi> and ſo require him either
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170659:38"/> to make ſome briefe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his Faith, as the Eunuch did, or elſe <hi>to give an anſwer to him that ſhall aske him a reaſon of the hope that is in him with meekneſſe and feare,</hi> according as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts Chriſtians to doe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 15.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="51-102" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, would you have a man to do this that hath received the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament many a time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, if he never yet did it, yea and although he have already done it in private, yet do I thinke it meet that hee ſhould goe before the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and Elders, and do
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170659:39"/> it againe to them more publikely.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed Sir, I doe confeſſe it is meet that all Ignorant perſons, who are not able to examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ought to doe ſo. But as for ſuch as have a great meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and ſo are able to examine themſelves, I ſee no need of it at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But I do conceive that it is meet for them alſo to come to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that ſo the Elderſhip may have a full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning their fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo far forth as they are able to judge, yea and that they themſelves may by their approbation bee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170659:39"/> the better confirmed in the ſame; yea, and that the ignorant ſort, who for want of knowledge are turned backe, may have no occaſion given them to ſay, That the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Elders are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, and that ſuch a man or ſuch a woman would be found as ignotant as they, if they were exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I doe now beginne to conceive that it is meet for a godly and learned Miniſter to examine a man, but I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee it lawfull nor needfull that thoſe whom you call Elders ſhould have any hand in ſuch a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170659:40"/> buſineſſe, eſpecially ſuch ignorant men as ſome of them are to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſſure your ſelfe it is both lawfull and needfull that there ſhould be Elders to joyne with the Miniſter both in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting thoſe to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament that upon exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination are conceived to be fit; and in keeping thoſe back who upon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination are conceived to bee unfit, becauſe Chriſt hath not given this power to the Miniſter alone, for when he ſaith, <hi>Matthew 18. 17. Tell the Church,</hi> hee doth not meane the Miniſter only,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170659:40"/> neither yet the whole Church, but the Rulers in the Church, to wit, the Miniſter and Elders; and ſo the Apoſtle men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning the excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the inceſtuous perſon, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6. ſaith, <hi>That his puniſhment was inflicted by many,</hi> not by the Miniſter onely, for then he would have ſaid by one; nor yet by the whole Church, for then he would have ſaid by all: but <hi>by many;</hi> that is to ſay, of the Presbytery, which conſiſted of many Officers. And indeed I do conceive it is very need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that the Elders ſhould be joyned with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170659:41"/> in this worke, both for the aſſiſting and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him therein, and for the preventing of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of ſuſpicion of his uſurping more power to himſelfe then Chriſt hath given unto him, or going beyond the bounds which Chriſt hath ſet him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, there is a Neighbour of mine, who is the Independant way (as it is called) who hath (to tell you truly) perſwaded with me to come into their way, and in our Conference toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I remember amongſt the reſt he told me, that by the word Church is not to be underſtood the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170659:41"/> Miniſters and Elders only, but alſo every member of the Church, and that it is therefore meet that every member of the Church ſhould joyne with the Miniſters and Elders, both in admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be conceived to be fit, and in keeping thoſe backe who upon examination are concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be unfit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I know who that Neighbour is of whom you ſpeake, and I hope he is a man truly fearing God; but yet I muſt tell you, that I am confident that therein he erreth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170659:42"/> from the truth, for it is evident by Scripture, that in the Church of Chriſt there are to be ſome Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours and Rulers, whom others in the Church muſt honour, be obedient unto, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28. the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God hath ſet ſome in the Church to be helpers in Government.</hi> And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 8. there is mention made of Rulers in the Church, <hi>He that ruleth,</hi> ſaith the text, <hi>let him doe it with diligence.</hi> And in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. the Apoſtle ſaith expreſly, <hi>Let the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that rule well be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worthy of double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170659:42"/> eſpecially they who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the word and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> and in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. it is ſaid, <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves unto them, becauſe they watch for your ſoules as they that muſt give an account.</hi> And moſt plainely it is ſaid, <hi>Heb. 13. 24. Salute all them that have the rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you, and all the Saints.</hi> Where you ſee, that Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Saints are made contra diſtinct one to another, and thus you ſee it is evident by all theſe Scriptures, that in the Church of Chriſt there are to be ſome Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Rulers, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170659:43"/> ſome to be ruled and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, but if all the members of the Church ſhould have an equall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in the Churches affaires, then ſhould they be all Officers and Rulers, and then who ſhould be ruled? If all were Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, then where were the governed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I muſt confeſſe that you have hereby given me more ſatisfaction in this point then ever any man yet did, and truly if I did make any queſtion of my fitneſſe to come to the Sacrament, I could be contented either to be examined by you private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170659:43"/> or elſe come before you and the Elders more publiquely, but that I thanke God I doe not, and therefore I cannot bring my heart to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto any ſuch thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Neighbour <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> let me tell you plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and truly, it is poſſible that a man may have a very great meaſure of knowledge, and leade a very righteous courſe of life according to the Law, and yet have no true faith in Chriſt, and ſo be unfit to come to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; for the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> when he was a Phariſee, and before he had any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170659:44"/> true faith in Chriſt at all, was endued with a great meaſure of knowledge, and legall righteouſneſſe, being as himſelfe confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, <hi>Act.</hi> 22. 3. brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and taught according to the perfect manner of the law of the Fathers, and as touching the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which is in the law he was blameleſſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 6.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, though the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> when he was a Phariſee, had a great meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet had he no knowledge of Chriſt, as thankes be to God we Chriſtians have in theſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170659:44"/> dayes, and therefore it is no marvell though he had no faith in him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell you neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Simon,</hi> that in theſe dayes of Goſpell light, a man may have a great meaſure of knowledge concerning Chriſts Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Chriſts Offices, Chriſts Death and Reſurrection, &amp; yet all may be but meer notions floting in the braine, and ſo indeed have no more true faith in Chriſt then <hi>Paul</hi> had when he was a Phariſee, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of ſome in his time that had <hi>eſcaped the pollutions of the world,</hi> and that <hi>through the knowledge of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170659:45"/> the Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and yet afterwards were intangled and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 20.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, I ſhould thinke it were impoſſible for a man that is able to anſwer you any queſtion, touching any fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall point of Religion, and that leades an honeſt and religious courſe of life to want true faith in Chriſt, for me thinkes it ſhould be as evident, that ſuch a man hath true faith, as it is evident, that a ſinfull and ungodly man hath it not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No, it is not ſo evident, for though it be true, that whatſoever
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170659:45"/> doth not gliſter is not gold, yet it is not ſo true that whatſoever doth gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is gold; even ſo may we ſay, That although it be evident, that every perſon that is groſly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and is a groſſe ſinner, hath not true faith in Chriſt, yet it is not ſo evident that every man that hath knowledge, and leades an honeſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous courſe of life accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law hath true faith in Chriſt, I tell you truly, a man <hi>may have a name that he liveth, and yet be dead;</hi> as it is ſaid concerning the Church of Sardis, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3. 1. yea, and a man may with the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170659:46"/> Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> think himſelfe <hi>rich, and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with goods, and to have need of nothing, and yet be wretched and miſerable, and poore, and blinde, and naked, Rev.</hi> 3. 17. and therefore I would intreat you to conſider well of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I doe perceive by that which you ſaid to me the other day, and by your words to me now, that you are ſomewhat jealous of me, though I hope there is no cauſe; but Sir, may not both you and the Elders be deceived in a man though you doe examine him, either in thinking a man hath faith in Chriſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170659:46"/> when he hath not, or in thinking he hath no faith when he hath?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, I thinke it is poſſible that we may be deceived both wayes, for we have none of us the ſpirit of infali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then Sir, me thinkes it ſhould be in vaine for a man to come before you to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No, not ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for though it be poſſible that we may be deceived, yet conſidering the courſe that we take in our way of examining, I hope we are ſeldome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, if at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170659:47"/>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Sir, I pray tell me what courſe you take.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why when any one commeth before us to be examined, we firſt of all deſire him either to make ſome briefe Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his faith, or elſe to anſwer us ſome Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which we ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto him, and if a man give us ſatisfaction concerning his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then we aske him what evidences he can ſhew of his Converſion, or New Birth, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of his true faith in Chriſt; and if he alſo
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170659:47"/> give us ſatisfaction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, then if we know not his life and converſation we make inquiry of it, and when we have ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction touching that alſo, we doe admit him to the Sacrament.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely Sir, I doe like this very well, and therefore becauſe you ſeeme to queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I have true faith in Chriſt or no, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented (now I am here) to give you leave to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine me, if you thinke good to take the paines.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, I am very willing to doe it for your good, and therefore I pray you in the firſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170659:48"/> place tell me, Who made the world, and all things therein?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>God is a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, infinite and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And how many Gods be there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>There is but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one true God, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And in what an eſtate did God create man at the firſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>He created him holy and righteous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And did man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in that holy &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous eſtate?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170659:48"/>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>O no, he fell from it by breaking of Gods expreſſe Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in eating of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And was the firſt man onely guilty of that ſinne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>O no, all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde did alſo become guilty in that they were all of them then in his Loynes, yea, they are not onely become guilty by having his ſinne impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto them, but they are alſo become filthy, by having his corruption in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment are all Mankind made liable and ſubject
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170659:49"/> unto by reaſon of their guiltineſſe and filthineſſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Even to eternall death and damnation in Hell fire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſhall all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde then partake of that puniſhment?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>O no, for God hath from all Eternity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and choſen ſome to eternall life and glory, and all thoſe ſhall certainely be ſaved.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>And by what meanes ſhall they be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Onely by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>He is the eternall
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170659:49"/> Son of God, who in time became Man for his Elect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what hath Chriſt done for their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>He hath fulfilled the Law, and ſuffered death for them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And by what meanes are the elect made partakers thereof?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Onely by meanes of faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a ſpeciall gift and grace of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed onely upon Gods elect, and wrought in their hearts by the power of his Spirit, whereby they doe receive and apply Chriſt unto themſelves particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170659:50"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a ſigne or a ſeale, wherein by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters bleſſing, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of Bread and Wine according to the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt is ſignified, exhibited, and ſealed to the faithfull Receiver, the nouriſhment of the ſoule to eternall life, by the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt crucified, and ſo his further confirmation in the covenant of grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And doe you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to come before me and the Elders when we are together, and ſo to be admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170659:50"/> the next time it ſhall be adminiſtred?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe deſire to partake of the Sacrament, but I am not yet very willing to be examined any more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And why doe you deſire to partake of the Sacrament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I doe conceive it is a duty which God requireth at my hands, and which tends much to the comfort and benefit of my ſoule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> I like all theſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers well except it be the laſt, how ever, ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers as theſe, though 'tis true they are all funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalls,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170659:51"/> yet if as they come from you they be rather Catechiſticall then experimentall, if they come onely from your head, and not alſo from your heart, it matters not greatly whether they had been better or worſe; for in a Catechiſticall manner a man may anſwer better, and yet want faith in Chriſt; and he may not anſwer ſo well, and yet have faith in Chriſt; and therefore for a more ſure Teſtimony of your faith in Chriſt, I would pray you to let me heare what heart knowledge you have, let me heare what Evidences you can
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170659:51"/> ſhew for your Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or new Birth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, whilſt I was a young man and unmarried I was very wilde, and given to much vanity, and many ſinfull courſes; but when I came to be a married man I left them all, and betooke my ſelfe to a very civill courſe of life, dealing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly and juſtly with all men, not doing the leaſt wrong to any, being very diligent in my Calling, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring thereby to get where withall to maintaine my ſelfe and my Family, and to bring up my children in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and good manners,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170659:52"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170659:52"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170659:53"/> and to keepe my ſelfe out of debt and danger, and to live in credit and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion amongſt my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and though I ſay it my ſelfe, I did ſo, and had the love of all that knew me, eſpecially of the poorer ſort, for the truth is, I was good to them: and I was alſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefull to goe to the Church every Sabbath day, and to ſee that my wife, children, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants did the like, and when we came home I did uſually read a Chapter either before or after ſupper, commanding my children and ſervants to doe the like, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170659:53"/> we uſed to ſing a Pſalm together, and then I commonly went to Prayer with them, though I muſt confeſſe I then did it upon a Booke; and this courſe of life I led for the ſpace of full ſeven yeeres together, and now Sir, before I goe any further, I would intreat you to tell me, what ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition you thinke I was in at this time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why the ſtate and condition that you were in at this time, ſo farre as I can perceive, was neither better nor worſe then the ſtate and condition of a meere ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill honeſt man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170659:54"/>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, herein you and I doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, for ever ſince it pleaſed the Lord to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten me, I have thought juſt ſo of my ſelfe, and yet whilſt I was in that condition, I thought my ſelfe to be in the onely happy condition, I meane as touching my ſoule, for I thought that he that came ſhort of me, and did not ſo much as I, did not ſo much as he ought to doe, and he that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond me, and did more then I, did more then he need to doe; but at laſt I heard a godly Miniſter handle theſe words, <hi>Mat. 5. 20. For I ſay unto you,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170659:54"/> that except your righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe exceed the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye ſhall in no wiſe enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven.</hi> Whence he tooke occaſion to ſhew what their righteouſneſſe was, and how farre they went, whereby I did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that they had gone further then I, and that in many things I come ſhort of them; whereupon I thought with my ſelfe, if I come ſhort of them that come ſhort of Heaven, ſurely I muſt either goe further, or elſe I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170659:55"/>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then I chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged my minde, yea, and my courſe of life alſo; for whereas before I thought ſuch men as were more zealous and forward in Religion then I was, they went too farre, and made more adoe then was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and were more nice then wiſe. Why now I ſaw I was deceived, for they were the onely men that ſhould enter into the Kingdome of Heaven; and thereupon I fell to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Sermons, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the Sabbath Day, but alſo on the Weeke day, and fell to writing after the Miniſter, and to make repitition of the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170659:55"/> Sermon when I came home, and on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day I did ordinarily aske my children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants what they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and whereas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I uſed to pray in my Family onely every Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath Day at night, why now I fell to the doing of it both morning and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning every day in the weeke, and without a Booke, yea, and I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded both my children and ſervants to learne a Catechiſme or two by heart, and to tell you the truth, I alſo did learne them my ſelfe, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before I did uſually ſweare by my faith and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170659:56"/> troth, thinking them to be no Oathes, and to tell a lye now and then for advantage, thinking that alſo to be no ſinne, why now I left thoſe things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; and whereas before I had no delight to keepe company with religious honeſt men, why now they were the onely men whoſe company I deſired; and thus have I gone on ever ſince I thanke God, and increaſed more and more both in knowledge and in godly converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo that time as I did conceive was the time of my true Converſion, or of my Regeneration and new Birth; and now Sir,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170659:56"/> I pray you tell me what you thinke of me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſurely you have done well both in turning from being a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane man, to be a civill honeſt man, and in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from being a civil ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man to be a religious honeſt man (as you terme it) but yet you have done ill in reſting in either, as it appeares you have done in both; for as you were kept from religious ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty by reſting in civill honeſty, ſo are you kept from Chriſt by reſting in religious honeſty, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reſting in ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and religious forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170659:57"/>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you then Sir, tell me what you would have me to doe more, for I doe aſſure you I cannot tell what to doe more then I have already done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly, I would have you to take off your heart from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and putting confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in your owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and reſt and put confidence in the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, for that is the way to have true faith in Chriſt, and to be juſtified in the ſight of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Sir, doe you not thinke that I who have led, and doe ſtill
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170659:57"/> lead ſuch a juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous courſe of life, am already juſtified in the ſight of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, neighbour <hi>Simon.</hi> I feare you are of the ſame opinion touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this point of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which I well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, old Maſter <hi>Culverwell,</hi> who wrot the Treatiſe of Faith, once told me ſome legall Profeſſours were, who uſing to come to him for reſolution in ſome points, would tell him, that they could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve their Juſtification, and Salvation, becauſe they were ſo ſinfull and ungodly; whereupon he would aſke them, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170659:58"/> they thought GOD would juſtifie the godly or the ungodly, they would preſently anſwer, the godly ſure; nay would he ſay, You are deceived, for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 5. That <hi>God juſtifieth the ungodly;</hi> even ſo, if you did conceive that you were a ſinfull and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, I am confident you would not beleeve that God hath juſtified you, but becauſe you doe conceive you are a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and godly man, therefore you thinke that you are already juſtified.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I would pray you to tell me what it is to juſtifie, or wherein
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170659:58"/> doth juſtification conſiſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The word juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie is in Scripture taken two wayes; Firſt, it is taken for GODS Act in making of a man juſt: Secondly, it is taken for Gods Act in pronouncing of a man juſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, and doth not Gods Act in making of a man juſt, goe before his Act in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of him juſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, for God being a juſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge, cannot in Juſtice pronounce any man juſt till he have firſt made him ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, how or what ſence can it be ſaid,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170659:59"/> that God juſtifieth the ungodly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 5. That <hi>God juſtifieth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly,</hi> is to be underſtood onely of the firſt Act of God in making of a man juſt, and not alſo of his ſecond Act in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of him juſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But then Sir, doth God make any man juſt whom he doth not alſo pronounce juſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God doth make juſt, he doth alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce juſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, why doe you ſeeme to blame me for being perſwaded,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170659:59"/> that God who hath made me juſt, hath alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced me juſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The reaſon why I blame you is, for that you doe imagine with the Papiſts, that God maketh a man juſt or righteous, by infuſing of Juſtice or Righteouſneſſe into him, whereas the truth is, God maketh him juſt or righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, by imputing the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt unto him, according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 5. 19. By the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of one ſhall many be made righteous;</hi> or which is all one, God maketh a man juſt or righteous by not imputing ſinne unto
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170659:60"/> him, but pardoning and forgiving all his ſinnes for Chriſts ſake, according to the ſaying of the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>Rom. 4. Verſe 6, 7, 8. Even as</hi> David <hi>deſcribeth the bleſſedneſſe of the man unto whom God impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth righteouſneſſe without workes,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſinnes are covered; bleſſed is the man unto whom the Lord will not impute ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, this Act of God, in thus making a man righteous I doe not well underſtand, and therefore I pray you tell me, what is meant by Gods imputing the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170659:60"/> of Chriſt unto a man, or not imputing his ſins unto him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is nothing elſe but this, to wit, that God graciouſly accepteth for a man, and in his behalfe, the Righteouſneſſe of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, both active, that is his obedience, which in the dayes of his fleſh he performed for man; and paſſive, that is, his ſufferings which he ſuſtained for man, as if he had in his owne perſon both done and ſuffered the ſame for himſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, if the Righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt be imputed to a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170659:61"/> man for his Juſtification, and a man be juſtified thereby, why then is it ſaid in Scripture, That <hi>Faith is imputed to a man for his righteouſneſſe,</hi> and that a man is juſtified thereby?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>It is becauſe faith is the inſtrument, and as it were the hand where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Chriſt and his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is received, ſo that whereſoever it is ſaid in Scripture, that <hi>Faith is imputed to a man for his righteouſneſſe,</hi> or, <hi>that a man is juſtified by faith,</hi> we are to underſtand it relatively, that is, as it hath relation to Chriſt and his Righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170659:61"/> which it receiveth and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth; for indeed Faith conſidered in it ſelfe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be imputed, neither as it is a habit, nor as it is an act, becauſe that which is within a man cannot be ſaid to be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Piſcator</hi> on Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> to a man, but that which is without a man; but faith is within a man, for, <hi>With the heart man beleeveth, Rom.</hi> 10. 10. and therefore faith can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be properly ſaid to be imputed to a man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, this may ſerve for a briefe and full anſwer to<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard</hi> in his ſound Beleever. pag. 228.</note> your queſtion, that to be juſtified by faith, and to be juſtified by Chriſts Righteouſneſſe, is all one
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170659:62"/> in Scripture phraſe and meaning, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 16, 17.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, if faith doe receive and apply the Righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, then it ſhould ſeeme that Gods imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not ſufficient for mans Juſtification with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faiths application.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, for without mans application Gods imputation is not at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then Sir, it ſhould ſeeme that a man doth helpe to juſtifie himſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>O no, not ſo, for mans application is alſo<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus</hi> Catechiſ.</note> from God, for God firſt imputeth unto a man
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170659:62"/> Chriſts ſatisfaction, and then he ingendreth faith in him, whereby he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes that which is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto him, and then is a man perfectly juſt or righteous indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, you have ſufficiently declared wherein that firſt Act of God conſiſteth, in making a man juſt and righteous, I pray you alſo ſhew wherein the ſecond Act of God conſiſteth, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing him juſt and righteous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>This Act of God is nothing elſe but a judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall acquiting, whereby the Lord as a Judge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth juſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170659:63"/> him that is accuſed and brought to the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat; and this is done when that Satan accuſeth, and the Law condemneth a Beleever, unto whom the Lord doth not impute ſinne, but doth abſolve and free him both from the fault and puniſhment; and this is that which the Apoſtle meaneth when he faith, <hi>Rom. 8. 33. It is God that juſtifieth, who is he that condemneth;</hi> where you ſee, that Juſtification is manifeſtly oppoſed to condemnation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I doe now plainely perceive, that a man is neither
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170659:63"/> made juſt by, nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced juſt for his owne inherent righteouſneſſe, but onely by and for Chriſts righteouſneſſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted; but Sir, Doth not the Lord whereſoever he imputes righteouſneſſe to a man, whereby he is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, infuſe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe alſo into him where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is ſanctified?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, for Chriſt by his obedience hath not onely obtained imputation of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for his elect, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are juſtified, but alſo that by his Spirit, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with faith, there ſhould be righteouſneſſe infuſed into them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170659:64"/> they are ſanctified, and therefore I doe affirme, that ſanctification is a neceſſary and unſeparable conſequent of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent righteouſneſſe be no part of that righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wherewith a man is formally juſtified, yet that righteouſneſſe wherewith a man is formally juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, is not imputed and applyed to any man that is growne in yeares of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, without the gift of inherent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereby he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 24. Coloſ. 3. 9.</note> in the ſpirit of his minde, and reſtored to the Image of God, which conſiſteth in knowledge,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170659:64"/> righteouſneſſe, and true holineſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, it ſeemes that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe whereby a man is juſtified, and the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe whereby he is ſanctified are not both one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, they are both one in regard of matter and ſubſtance, but yet there are divers other differences betwixt them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you Sir, for my better informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhew we what thoſe differences are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why firſt of all, the righteouſneſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Beleever is juſtified is in Scripture, called, Gods
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170659:65"/> righteouſneſſe, as you may ſee, <hi>Rom. 1. 17. Rom.</hi> 3. 21. not becauſe it is the righteouſneſſe of the God-head, but becauſe it is the righteouſneſſe of that Perſon who is God: but the righteouſneſſe whereby he is ſanctified is called mans owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, as you may ſee, <hi>Rom. 12. 3. Phil.</hi> 3. 9.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe whereby a man is juſtified, is called the righteouſneſſe which is of faith, but the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe whereby he is ſanctified is called, the righteouſneſſe which is of the Law, as you may ſee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 5, 6.</p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170659:65"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereby a Beleever is juſtified, is inherent in Chriſt, and imputed unto him, but the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereby he is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied is inherent in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, being infuſed into him by the Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe whereby a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever is juſtified, is a moſt perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cannot be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, nor admit of any degrees, for the God-head of Chriſt afforded ſuch dignity, vertue, effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, and merit to the obedience and ſufferings of his Man-hood, as that
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170659:66"/> they were an all-ſufficient price, ranſome, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the Juſtice of God; but the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whereby he is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied is imperfect, and there are degrees of it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of grace received.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, to name no more, the righteouſneſſe whereby a Beleever is juſtified, is alwaies im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted unto him, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the righteouſneſſe whereby he is ſanctified is infuſed into him by the Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="102-155" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly Sir, I muſt acknowledge that I did never before this time
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170659:66"/> obſerve theſe differences, betweene this two-fold righteouſneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> if I miſtake not, there are two ſorts of Profeſſors, who for want of the true underſtanding of this difference, doe confound this two-fold righteouſneſſe, making them to be both one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you Sir, let me know who theſe Profeſſors be, and what they doe, that ſo I may know whether I be one of them or no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why one ſort of them, of whom I thinke meet to ſpeake firſt, are ſuch as may be truly called
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170659:67"/> Antinomiſticall Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, who confound the righteouſneſſe of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Juſtification, in making them to be both one, for they will have that righteouſneſſe which is inherent in Chriſt to be the righteouſneſſe both of their Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of their Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; they will have all righteouſneſſe to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in Chriſt, and no righteouſneſſe to be inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in themſelves, they will have God to impute all righteouſneſſe unto them, but not infuſe any righteouſneſſe into them, they will apply a perfect
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170659:67"/> righteouſneſſe unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by faith; when as they have neither faith nor righteouſneſſe, they will have Chriſt without his Spirit, and ſo indeed have neither Chriſt nor his Spirit; you ſhall heare theſe men and women in their conference with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers about theſe points, will be ever uttering theſe or the like ſpeeches; As for me, truly I have nothing in me that is good, but am wholly ſinfull; neither doe I looke for any thing elſe to be in me but ſinne, and yet I doe verily beleeve, that I am perfectly righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in the ſight of God
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170659:68"/> through Chriſt, or in Chriſt, being cloathed with a garment of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and covered with a robe of Righteouſneſſe, ſo that I am all faire and cleane, and there is no ſpot in me.</p>
                  <p>Theſe men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, becauſe they are not to looke for any good in themſelves, as a ground or cauſe of their faith, they will not looke for any good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as an evidence of faith, becauſe they are not to looke for inherent righteouſneſſe before they have by faith apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the imputed righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; therefore they
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170659:68"/> will not looke for any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent righteouſneſſe at all, becauſe they muſt not looke for inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe to move them to beleeve, therefore they will not looke for it to aſſure them that they have beleeved.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely Sir, theſe men and women are much miſtaken, but what doe you thinke is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly, I have thought upon three Reaſons of it, as firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that they have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by meanes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading, or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, been inſtructed in the law of faith onely,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170659:69"/> without inſtruction in the law of workes going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or the Doctrine of the Law of Chriſts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after, or elſe in the Doctrine of the law of workes, and the law of faith without the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Law of Chriſt. My meaning is, they have been inſtructed, that they of themſelves are altogether unable ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to doe, or ſuffer that which the law as it is the covenant of workes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, and that they are therefore in a dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable condition, and that yet notwithſtanding, if they truly beleeve, and ſo apprehend the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170659:69"/> of Jeſus Chriſt, they ſhall have life and ſalvation, but they have not been inſtructed that if they doe truly beleeve, then they doe hereupon become ſubject and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the minde and will of Chriſt revealed in his Word; they have been inſtructed that he is Jeſus, a Saviour, but they have not been inſtructed that to whomſoever he is Jeſus, a Saviour, he is alſo to them Chriſt, a Lord.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe they take faith to be nothing elſe but a meere notion of Chriſt and his Righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170659:70"/> ſwimming in their braine, or at the beſt but a meere apprehenſion thereof in their minds, which is but a faith of their own forging, &amp; ſo they think they have a ſtrong faith, when as indeed they have not the leaſt meaſure or degree of a true weake faith; they thinke they have Chriſt in their hearts, when as indeed he is but in their heads; they thinke they have him in their wills and affections, when as indeed they have him but onely in their underſtandings.</p>
                  <p>And a third Reaſon is, becauſe they miſtake the meaning of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30. where he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170659:70"/> ſaith, that <hi>Chriſt is made unto us of God both righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for whereas they doe thence conclude, that Chriſts inherent righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is not onely that righteouſneſſe whereby a Beleever is juſtified, but alſo that righteouſneſſe whereby he is ſanctified; and that in a Beleever there is no inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, nor ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I have heard ſome have affirmed; the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Apoſtle is not ſo, but his meaning is; that God hath not onely ordained that Beleevers ſhould be juſtified by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the righteouſneſſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170659:71"/> which is inherent in Chriſt imputed unto them, but that Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſhould by his Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe righteouſneſſe into them, and ſo ſanctifie them; he having not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the merit of his Death procured the one, but alſo by the vertue of his Death procured the other, and ſo indeed is made unto them both righteouſneſſe and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; and thus have I ſhewed you the firſt ſort of thoſe Profeſſors, who confound his two-fold righteouſneſſe, and how they doe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I thanke God I am none of this
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170659:71"/> ſort, and therefore I pray you ſhew me alſo who are the ſecond ſort, and how they doe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, the ſecond ſort are ſuch as are truly called formall, or legall Profeſſors, who confound the righteouſneſſe of juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication with the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of ſanctification, making them to be both one; for they will have that righteouſneſſe which is inherent in man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or rather thoſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous actions which are performed and done by himſelfe, to be not only that righteouſneſſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he is ſanctified, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that righteouſneſſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170659:72"/> whereby he is juſtified; and hence it is that ſuch men doe labour and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to reforme their lives, and their waies, and to performe good duties, both towards God and man, and alſo to the end they may have a ground to build their faith upon, and ſo farre forth as they can ſee a righteous diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in themſelves, and righteous and religious actions performed by themſelves; why ſo farre forth they will beleeve that they are juſtified in the ſight of God, and no further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>And I pray you Sir, ſhew me alſo the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170659:72"/> ground and reaſon of this their miſtake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly I have alſo thought upon three Reaſons of this, whereof the firſt is, becauſe they either by meanes of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading, or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, have been inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in ſuch a manner in the Law of the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, as if a man in the time of this life were able to keepe and doe them perfectly, and ſo might be juſtified in the ſight of God by his owne obedience to them, and they have not been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and killed by the Law, in having it made knowne unto them in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170659:73"/> the purity and perfection of it.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Reaſon is, becauſe they have had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no inſtructions in the Doctrine of the Law of faith, or Covenant of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, eſpecially betwixt that covenant and the covenant of workes, or betwixt the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Juſtification, and the righteouſneſſe of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; and therefore being not able to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt them, they doe confound them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
                  <p>And a third reaſon is, becauſe man naturally ſees no other way to be juſtified and ſaved, but
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170659:73"/> onely by his own workes and performances, for as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith, It is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall opinion of the whole world, that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is gotten by the workes of the Law; and thus have I alſo ſhewed you the ſecond ſort of them that confound this two-fold righteouſneſſe, and how they doe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, as I doe conceive, he that doth confound this two-fold righteouſneſſe this latter way, doth not ſo ill, nor is not in ſo bad a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as he that doth it by the former way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed for ought I ſee, he doth even
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170659:74"/> every whit as ill, and is every whit in as bad a condition as the other; for as he that confounds the righteouſneſſe of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification with the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth thereby deſtroy them both to himſelfe, and ſo indeed hath nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them: ſo he that confounds the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Juſtification with the righteouſneſſe of Sanctification, doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deſtroy them both to himſelfe, and ſo indeed hath neither of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed Sir, it is evident to me, that he who hath not the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of ſanctification,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170659:74"/> hath not the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Juſtification, and ſo indeed hath neither of them: but Sir, me thinkes he who hath the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Sanctification, ſhould alſo have the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo indeed have both of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No, you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, it is not ſo, for as he that thinkes he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves, and ſo hath the Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt imputed unto him for his Juſtification, deceives himſelfe except the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Spirit of Chriſt be afterwards infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into him for his ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; even ſo he that
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170659:75"/> thinkes he leades a godly and righteous courſe of life, and ſo hath the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Spirit of Chriſt infuſed into him for his ſanctification de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives himſelfe, except the Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt hath been before imputed unto him for his juſtification.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I grant it, that a man may thinke he doth beleeve when he doth not, and therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himſelfe, becauſe that he cannot ſee his faith; but me thinkes a man ſhould not thinke he lives a godly and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous courſe of life when he doth not, becauſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170659:75"/> that is to be ſeene.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>O but let me tell you, as there is a forme of faith without the power of faith, which cauſed the Apoſtle to pray for the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> that <hi>God</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>would grant unto them the worke of faith with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer;</hi> even ſo is there a forme of godlineſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as you may ſee, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 5. And as this forme of faith is nothing elſe but a faith of a mans owne hammering, or of his owne acquiring, and ſo is but an acquired faith, and not an infuſed faith; even ſo this forme of godlineſſe is nothing elſe
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170659:76"/> but a godlineſſe of a mans owne hammering, or of his owne acquiring got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the improvement of his Naturall and Morall abilities, and ſo indeed is but a godlineſſe acquired, and not a godlineſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, it ſeems that a man cannot by having the one, be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he hath alſo the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, if he have them not both he hath neither of them, for as there is no imputed righteouſneſſe going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, where infuſed righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe followeth not after, ſo is there no infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170659:76"/> righteouſneſſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after, where imputed righteouſneſſe hath not gone before; ſo that if either of them be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and beare not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the other, and that in its due place, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods owne order, and as his owne di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct actions, they are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, I pray you tell me how a man may know that he hath them both, and that they doe beare witneſſe either to other, and that in their due place according to Gods owne order, and as his owne diſtinct actions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, if a man
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170659:77"/> have truly ſeene and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that in regard the Lord did in <hi>Adam</hi> Create all men righteous, and able to yeeld perfect obedience to his Law, they having all of them in him tranſgreſſed his Law; it is a righteous thing with God to require a full ſatisfaction to be made to his Juſtice, by a perfect obedience to his Law both actively and paſſively, before he doe forgive any mans iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or cover any mans ſinne, and ſo pronounce him juſt. And that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the infinite exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the glorious puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and abſolute perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170659:77"/> of the Law of God, he ſee an utter impoſſibility in himſelfe, to yeeld a perfect active obedience unto it, and that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of that infinite Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty that is offended, there is an infinite ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring required, which muſt either be an eternall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or that which is equivolent to eternall: And that man being a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit Creature can doe it no way but by an eternall puniſhment, and that therefore he ſees no way for himſelfe but Hell and Damnation; and if then it hath been revealed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that Jeſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, and of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170659:78"/> the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> was both God and Man in one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that therefore his Divine nature did ſo ſanctifie his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and did adde ſuch dignity, worth, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency to it, that he was thereby made a perſon of infinite value, and ſo by his holy and righteous courſe of life in the dayes of his fleſh, he fulfilled the Law perfectly, and by his Death and Blood-ſhed made an infinite ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to divine Juſtice, and all this as a Surety, and in the place and ſtead of all thoſe that truly beleeve on his name; and if he have thereupon truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170659:78"/> that all this was as truly done and ſuffered for him, as if he himſelfe had done and ſuffered it in his owne Perſon, and that he is thereby juſtified in the ſight of God, then may he be ſure that the righteouſneſſe that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in Chriſt hath been imputed unto him, and apprehended by faith, and ſo hath gone before as an Antecedent. And if he have thereupon ſeene, conſidered, and felt the great and free love and<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 5.</note> favour of God in Chriſt, ſhed abroad in his heart, by the Holy Ghoſt then given unto him, ſo as that his heart hath been
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170659:79"/> thereby moved, yea and conſtrained to love God<note place="margin">1 John 4. 19.</note> becauſe he hath loved him firſt; and out of love to deſire and endeavour to keepe his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo that whereas before this time he either lived a prophane and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſe of life, or a meere civill honeſt courſe of life, aiming onely or chiefly at his owne credit and profit in this world, or a religious honeſt courſe of life onely, or chiefly for his owne eternall wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare in the life to come.</p>
                  <p>If this <hi>grace of God, or this free love and favour of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 11, 12.</note> 
                     <hi>God in Chriſt hath ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared unto him, as that it
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170659:79"/> hath taught him to deny ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world,</hi> not for faith and juſtification, but from faith and juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; then may he be aſſured that inherent righteouſneſſe, wrought by the Spirit of Chriſt, hath followed as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently that he hath both the righteouſneſſe of juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of ſanctification, bearing witneſſe either to other in their due place, according to Gods owne order, and as his owne diſtinct actions.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170659:80"/>
                  <p>And now neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> I beſeech you try your ſelfe by theſe things, and know that if it hath been in any meaſure thus with you, then you may be aſſured that you have truly beleeved on the name of Jeſus Chriſt, and are juſtified freely by his grace, and ſanctified by his Spirit, and ſo are no formall or legall Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor; but if it hath been in no meaſure thus with you, but that you have laboured and endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to live a godly and righteous courſe of life, that ſo you might have a ground to build your faith upon, that is, upon your
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170659:80"/> owne righteouſneſſe and performances, if you have been <hi>ignorant of Gods righteouſneſſe,</hi> as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 3.</note> ſaith, the Jewes were, and have <hi>gone about to ſtabliſh your owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> as they did, then you may be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that you have not truly beleeved on the name of Jeſus Chriſt, neither are you juſtified nor ſanctified, but are in plaine tearmes a meere le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Profeſſor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that I have not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore been acquainted with theſe things, and therefore I cannot truly ſay that I have done thus,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170659:81"/> or that it hath been ſo with me, but yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be perſwaded that I have gone about to ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh mine owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, for I know right well, that when we have done all that we can we are but unprofitable ſervants, and that a man is to be juſtified by the mercies of God, and the merits of Chriſt, and not by his owne workes and merits, as the Papiſts hold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I but neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> I muſt tell you, that it is one thing to ſay thus in words, and to hold thus in judgement, and another thing to doe it in effect and practice; I
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170659:81"/> meane in heart and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, it is not enough for a man to thinke, and be of opinion that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſtified by his owne righteouſneſſe and performances, for that is onely a worke of the judgement rightly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and not a worke of the heart rightly refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; wherefore I doe admoniſh you to take heed, that whilſt you are a Proteſtant in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and profeſſion, you be not a Papiſt in effect and practice, I meane in the inward diſpoſition of your heart, as I feare me too many, both men and women in this City are;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170659:82"/> for if I be not miſtaken, their very ſpeeches and behaviour doe teſtifie, that becauſe they know and doe more then they do conceive others know and doe, or becauſe they are members of ſuch a mans Congregation, and ſo in a Church way as they call it, therefore <hi>they truſt in themſelves that they are righteous,</hi> as our Saviour ſaid the Phariſees did, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 9. and yet if a man ſhould ſay unto them as our Saviour did to the Phariſees, <hi>Luke 16. 15. Ye are they which juſtifie your ſelves,</hi> they would utterly deny it as you doe; but to tell you
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170659:82"/> plainly neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> your ſpeeches and behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, when you were with me the other day made me to feare that you were but a kind of a Phariſaicall Profeſſor, furely in your crowing over, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing your honeſt neighbour <hi>Zacheus;</hi> in compariſon of your ſelfe you did too nearely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, crowing over, and undervaluing the humble Publican, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. and in judging of him to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and unworthy to come to the Lords Table; you did too nearely reſemble <hi>Simon</hi> the Phariſee, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Luke</hi> the 7. who
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170659:83"/> when he ſaw that ſinfull, yet penitent and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving woman, <hi>waſhing our Saviours feet with her teares, and wiping them with the haires of her head,</hi> he ſpake within himſelfe ſaying, <hi>This man if he were a Prophet, would have knowne who, and what manner of woman this is that hath touched him, for ſhe is a ſinner,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray you conſider of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, this is ſomewhat ſtrange, that a man ſhould put confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in his owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and thinke he is thereby juſtified and yet not know it, I would
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170659:83"/> you could give me ſome ſignes of a mans doing ſo, that ſo I may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I doe ſo or no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly I can give you no more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter a ſigne of it then that which I have already given you, and that is in plaine termes a proud ſpirit, for thoſe men and women, that doe truly beleeve, <hi>that they are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 24</note> 
                     <hi>freely by Gods grace, through the redemption that is in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> they are the humbleſt people, and the moſt free from ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall pride of any people in the world; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle having fully proved free juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170659:84"/> in reſpect of a mans ſelfe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26. he breakes out in the next verſe into this patheticall expreſſion, ſaying, <hi>Where is boaſting then? it is excluded; by what law? of workes; nay, but by the law of faith.</hi> I tell you neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> if a true Beleevers heart doe begin to ſwell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his excelling o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in gifts and parts, he doth ere long give it a vent, by ſaying to it in the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 4. 7. Who maketh thee to differ from another, and what haſt thou that thou didſt not receive; now if thou didſt receive it,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170659:84"/> why doſt thou glory as if thou hadſt not received it?</hi> But yet to the intent you may be the more fully convinced, that you have put confidence in your owne righteouſneſſe, I pray you anſwer me this queſtion; Did you ever finde it a hard matter to deny your owne righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, to become truly poore in ſpirit, to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off from confidence in your owne perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, and to paſſe through them all to Jeſus Chriſt? I beſeech you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me truly from your heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, I muſt confeſſe I never
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170659:85"/> thought my ſelfe guilty of any ſuch thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it you are guilty of it, for it is naturall for every man and woman, when they leave off plod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding towards Hell in the dirty path of ſinne, yet to goe on thitherward in the cleaner path of duty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in; when Satan can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keepe a man from Chriſt by ſinne, then he labours to keep him from him by ſelfe; if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keep a man with his ſinnes from fleſh-pots in Aegypt, then he labours to keep him from <hi>Canaan,</hi> by loſing himſelfe, and his ſoule in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170659:85"/> of his owne perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances reſted in, aſsure your ſelfe that there is in all men naturally this frame of ſpirit, never to come to Chriſt whilſt they have any hopes that their owne performances will heale them, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here they reſt untill they ſee it, bewaile it, and pray againſt it; and therefore if you never did ſo, it is cleare that you doe put confidence in your owne performances. Againe, I pray you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer me another queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truly; and that is, Did you ever ſee ſo many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and ſo much rottenneſse and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170659:86"/> as touching the manner and end of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming duties that you have even loathed your ſelfe, and have been wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and tired in your owne endeavours by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>No truly Sir, I cannot ſay I have, for I have alwaies had great delight in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of religious exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I doe aſsure you this is another ſigne that you have reſted and put confidence in your owne performances, for till a man ſee, and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his wandring and worldly thoughts, and of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170659:86"/> his drowſineſse and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſse, if not ſleepineſse in Prayer, and hearing the Word, and ſuch like exerciſes; and till he ſee, and take notice of his ſelfe ends in doing good actions he will reſt, and put confidence in them, and be thereby kept from Chriſt; and beleeve it neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> before that a man doe take up his reſt in Chriſt, the Lord doth diſcover unto him ſo much imperfections in his owne performances, that he cryes out within himſelfe, I ſee now what a vile undone wretch I am, I can doe nothing well; all that I am is vile,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170659:87"/> and all that I doe is vile; I ſee now that I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed poore, and blinde, and naked; and hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he is quite tired out, and ſits down wearie, not ſeeing any hopes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the breach betweene God and himſelfe, and this ſaith a godly Writer I take to be the meaning of <hi>Mat. 11. 28. Yea that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards</hi> ſound Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever. p. 134.</note> you that are weary in your owne way, in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king reſt to your ſoules by your owne hard labour, or workes, as the word ſignifies, and are tired out therein, and ſo are now <hi>laden</hi> indeed with ſinne, and the heavie preſſure of that finding no eaſe by all
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170659:87"/> that you doe, <hi>Come to me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>&amp; you ſhall</hi> then <hi>finde reſt unto your ſoules.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, I pray you let me aske you one queſtion more, and that is this; Have you not prized the bare performances of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wonderfully; that is, Have you not thought when you have prayed ſo many times in a day, and heard ſo many Sermons in a weeke, and turned to all the places of Scripture that the Miniſter hath co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and folded downe the leafe in your Bible, or elſe writ their Sermons after them, and made ſome repetition thereof to others, and the like; I
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170659:88"/> ſay, have you not in ſo doing reſted ſatisfied, without looking for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of your Prayers, or what good you have gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to your owne ſoule by your hearing, and ſo whether you have met with God in Chriſt, in all theſe waies and meanes, I pray you anſwer me truly from your heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Beleeve me Sir, I muſt confeſſe I have done ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I beſeech you take this as another evident ſigne of your reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and putting confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in your owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, for if a man doe not put confidence
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170659:88"/> therein, then he makes uſe of ſuch performances, but onely as a Bridge or Ferry-boat to carry or waft him over to God in Chriſt, and reſteth not contented till hee bee brought thither; other ſignes I might lay downe touching this matter, but I hope theſe will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for you to try your ſelfe by, if the Lord be pleaſed to make them ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, and ſuppoſe that I ſhould thereby finde that I have been guilty of reſting and relying upon mine owne duties and performances, and ſhould come before
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170659:89"/> you and the Elders, and acknowledge the ſame, would you thereupon conclude me to be but a formall legall Profeſſor without true faith in Chriſt, and therefore not fit to be admitted to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Neighbour <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> to the intent you may more clearely ſee and perceive what we doe when we meet together, and alſo declare it unto others if you ſee occaſion, I pray you underſtand and take notice, that if we upon examination finde a man to be wholly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and wholly ſinfull,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170659:89"/> as you know I found our neighbour <hi>Alexander</hi> to be, then we doe abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude that he hath no true faith in Chriſt, and therefore we ſhut the Gate againſt him, and keepe him from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament under the notion of an ignorant &amp; prophane man, and ſuffer him not to come there whilſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in that condition.</p>
                  <p>Yea, and though we know a man that he lives honeſtly and peaceably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his neighbours, and deales uprightly and juſtly with all men, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving every man his due, and for ought we know or can heare is free from all
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170659:90"/> groſſe and ſcandalous ſins, yet if upon examination we finde him to be groſly ignorant, then doe we likewiſe conclude, that he hath no true faith in Chriſt, and ſo ſhut the Gate againſt him alſo, and keepe him from the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament under the notion or a meere civill honeſt man, and ſuffer him not to come there whilſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in that condition.</p>
                  <p>But if upon examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we finde a man to have a competent meaſure of knowledge, eſpecially if it be experimentall of himſelfe, and neither know, nor can upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry heare any thing to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170659:90"/> the contrary, but that he leads both a civill and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious honeſt courſe of life, though he be accuſed to be but a formall le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Profeſſor; yea, and though we upon exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation doe finde him not to be ſo cleare and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct in his knowledge touching the difference betwixt the Law and the Goſpell, or Covenant of workes and Covenant of Grace, as we could wiſh he were; yea, and though for want of ſo cleare a light betwixt Juſtification and Sanctification, as ſome have, he ſeemes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the righteouſneſſe of juſtification with the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170659:91"/> righteouſneſſe of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, yet if he be an humble man, &amp; ſhew it by confeſſing his ignorance, and his willingneſſe to be better inſtructed herein; then we judge in charity that he hath true faith in Chriſt, and ſo open the gate of the Sacrament and let him in; but if upon examination we finde a man ignorant in theſe points, and yet becauſe of his great meaſure of knowledge in others, though not ſo neceſſary points to be knowne, he be puffed up, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his righteous courſe of life be kept back from ſeeing his need of Chriſt,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170659:91"/> as it ſeemes to me you are, then are we <hi>jealous over</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. ii. 2</note> 
                     <hi>him with godly jealouſie,</hi> as the Apoſtle was over the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> but yet we dare not abſolutely conclude that he hath no true faith in Chriſt, and therefore we pray him, as I doe now pray you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you come to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, to <hi>command with your owne heart upon your bed,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> exhorts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 4. and to <hi>examine himſelfe,</hi> as you know the Apoſtle exhorts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 28. and if he come unto us againe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious examination of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe he hath found, that
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170659:92"/> that with zealous <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his converſion, he hath counted his owne righteouſneſſe and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers to be <hi>gaine,</hi> that is to ſay, that he hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto reſted and put con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in them, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be juſtified in the ſight of God by them, but now with him he counted them loſſe for Chriſt, and deſired to be found in <hi>him, not having his owne righteouſneſſe which is of the Law, but</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which is of God through faith,</hi> then doe wee willingly open the doore and let him in;
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170659:92"/> otherwiſe we ſend not for him againe, and even ſo are we like to deale by you.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="155-202" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, you have anſwered me fully, and I hope I ſhall thinke of it; but Sir, ſuppoſe that an Antinomiſticall Profeſſor ſhould come before you, how would you deale with him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why though a man be accuſed to be an Antimonian, yet if upon examination we finde that he hath a competent meaſure of knowledge, and we neither know nor can heare but that he leades an honeſt and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious courſe of life,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170659:93"/> though he ſeeme to hold, that the Law is not to be a rule of life to a Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and that God can ſee no ſin in a juſtified per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that God is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther angry, nor doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict his people for ſinne, and that Chriſts inherent righteouſneſſe is both the righteouſneſſe of a Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers juſtification and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; yet if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that he doth not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily and obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hold and maintaine theſe points, but is rather induced to hold them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch a Miniſter, or ſuch a religious man whom he doth reverence and hath a good opinion
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170659:93"/> of is that judgement, and be willing to be inſtructed in the truth, then doe we hope that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this he hath true faith in Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe open the gate to him and let him in; but if upon information and examination we finde a man to hold and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine theſe points obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, and doe either certainely know or heare that his converſion is not ſuch as becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt, then we doe very much ſuſpect him, though he have a great meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and therefore doe not preſently open the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170659:94"/> gate unto him, but pray him to hearken to the truth, and conſider of it when he commeth home, and then if afterwards he come to us againe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his errours, and profeſſe his griefe and ſorrow for the ſame, then doe we willingly open the doore unto him, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſend not for him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, if you be ſo carefull and ſo ſtrict whom you doe admit to the Sacrament, then me thinkes ſome in this City, yea ſome in this Pariſh that I know ſhould come in amongſt you, and not goe the Independant way as they have a mitde to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170659:94"/> doe, for they tell me that the reaſon why they have no minde to come in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you is, becauſe you doe admit ſuch to the Sacrament as are not fit to be admitted; and to tell you the truth, I my ſelfe alſo had ſome thoughts of going that way, onely I reſolved to ſtay and ſee what your way would be, and what you would doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> though I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily perſwaded there be many men and women goe that way who doe truly feare the Lord, yet am I jealous that there are divers taken in amongſt
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170659:95"/> them, that are as unfit and as unmeet to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper as any that we have hitherto admitted; and therefore I ſee no reaſon that any Chriſtian hath to leave us, and goe to them for any ſuch cauſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you Sir, tell me what you thinke of the Independant way, for I would faine heare your judgement concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> I have neither minde nor time to fall upon any ſuch diſcourſe, neither would I adviſe you to trouble your ſelfe,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170659:95"/> nor ſpend your time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout any ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall matters as I doe conceive that is, but give rather diligence to make your calling and election ſure, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorts us; labour to know Jeſus Chriſt and him Crucified, and to know your ſelfe, and whether you be in the faith or no. There are too many people that doe ſpend too much time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſuch needleſſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and too many wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling diſputes have been thereby occaſioned; I wiſh with all my heart there might be no more, and I wiſh with all my
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170659:96"/> heart, that all who are truly godly either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them or us, had ſuch humble loving hearts as Chriſtians ought to have, that we might nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpeake nor thinke evill one of another, but rather ſtudy and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make up the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which are needleſly made betwixt us, that ſo if it were the Lords will we might <hi>all ſpeake the ſame thing, and that there might be no diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, but that we might be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement,</hi> according to the Apoſtles exhortation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170659:96"/> and that we <hi>might with one minde, and with one mouth glorifie God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 6. and ſo have more neare and ſweet communion toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all the Lords holy Ordinances, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and building up one another in our moſt holy faith; and thus you ſee what my minde and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is touching theſe things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Then Sir, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me that you doe not onely deſire that all thoſe that are godly, and have a minde to goe the Independant way, ſhould
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170659:97"/> come to you and joyne with you in your way, but alſo that all thoſe who are already joyned in the Independant way ſhould returne to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>That is my deſire indeed, and I doubt not but that it would be very well pleaſing and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Lord, if all that are truly godly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, whether they be Miniſters or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, would come in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us; for truly I can ſee no warrant they have from the Word of God to ſeparate from us, and to gather Churches out of Churches as they doe, ſurely, me thinkes if
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170659:97"/> they would but read that learned and moderate Tract, called, <hi>Jus Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> with an indifferent judgement, and moderate ſpirit, without prejudice, they ſhould ſee that our way touching Church-Government commeth as neare the minde and will of Chriſt as can be found out in his Word.</p>
                  <p>But what ſaid a godly, judicious, and moderate Miniſter of the Goſpell in the Pulpit not long ſince in my hearing, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded ſaid he, and it is not onely my judgement, but alſo the judgement of a grave, gody, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divine, who had
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170659:98"/> long ſtudied the point, that there is not to be found in all the whole New Teſtament a perfect Plat-forme of Church-Government, which makes me thinke (ſaid he) that it is not the mind of Chriſt that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians under the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament ſhould much bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie or trouble themſelves about ſuch matters. Theſe words as neare as I can remember he uttered, and truly I thinke it were well if we were all of his mind, that ſo we might buſie our mindes, and ſpend leſſe time about ſuch matters, and bend our mindes and ſtudies more about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170659:98"/> of ſubſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> about the Doctrine of Faith and Repentance, and matters that concerne Chriſtian practice, and godly converſation, and meekeneſſe, and love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves; truly neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> I am perſwaded that all, both godly Miniſters, and godly Chriſtians that doe now live in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, have great cauſe to rejoyce and be thankfull to the Lord, that hath let them live to ſee thoſe things which we ſee, to wit, that there is now po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer given to godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Elders, to keep back unfit and unworthy
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170659:99"/> Communicants from the Lords Table, the which it is well knowne hath not beene heretofore though much deſired; and O that the Lord would be pleaſed to move the hearts of all our godly diſcenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to come in and joyne themſelves with us, that ſo we might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and praiſe the name of the Lord toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but no more of this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly Sir, theſe your words have moved my heart to your way, and I wiſh I were worthy to come in amongſt you, but I will take my leave
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170659:99"/> of you, and goe home and conſider of what you have this day ſaid unto me concerning the ſtate and condition of my ſoule, for I ſtill feare I am not right; and I ſee that the chiefe thing to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked after and regarded is the true Knowledge of Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min</speaker>
                  <p>I ſurely, that is the thing indeed, and O that we could all of us ſeeke more after that then we doe, and as one in a<note place="margin">In <hi>Bacon</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Catachiſ. Epiſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory.</hi>
                     </note> certaine place ſaith very ſweetly; Oh that every one in this Kingdome, that truly deſires to feare the name of God, were ſo wiſe as to forbeare this
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170659:100"/> claſhing &amp; daſhing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in pieces one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another for matters externall, triviall, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantiall in Religion, and would at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with that which is alone ſaving and everlaſting, and account it honour and happineſſe enough in matters apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to God to be a Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>I remember I was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told by a Chriſtian friend of mine, that one comming to old Maſter <hi>Dod</hi> not long before his death, to deſire him to reſolve him about the point of Re-baptizing, or ſome ſuch like point; he
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170659:100"/> anſwered, Friend, have you made your Calling and Election ſure, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give diligence to make that ſure, which in my judgement was a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gracious anſwer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I will now take my leave of you for this time, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you pray for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> I would here breake off and take my leave of you, were it not that I ſee our neighbour <hi>Mathias</hi> looke very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily, and therefore I pray you tarry a while till I have ſpoken a few words unto him, and then I will take leave of you both
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170659:101"/> together. How doe you neighbor <hi>Mathias,</hi> what ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you to be ſo ſad, what is the matter with you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>O Sir, if you did but know how it is with me, you would ſay I had cauſe to be heavie and ſad.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Weepe not man, weepe not I pray you, but tell me what is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>O Sir, I am trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to thinke what will become of my ſoule when I dye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth this trouble?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, the hearing of your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Simon</hi> hath cauſed
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170659:101"/> it for (I thinke with my ſelfe) that if he that is a man of ſuch great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and holy life and converſation, be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by you, and doe queſtion himſelfe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be in a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or no; alas, then what may I thinke of my ſelfe, that am ſuch a poore ignorant and ſinfull man as I am?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But I hope you are neither ſo ignorant, nor ſo ſinfull as you thinke you are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>O yes Sir, it is too true, the Lord he knoweth it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, have you no knowledge in the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170659:102"/> points of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, did you never learne your Catechiſme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, when I was young I learned a little, but alas I have forgotten it long ſince.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I hope you doe remember ſome of it, and therefore I pray you tell me, what is God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>I beſeech you Sir, beare with my ignorance, and I will anſwer you as well as I can; I thinke God is the Maker and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of all things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſaid, and how many Gods be there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely Sir, I think there is but one true God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſaid, and
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170659:102"/> how many Perſons is there in the Trinity?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke Sir there are three.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And how are the three Perſons diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas Sir, I cannot tell how to anſwer that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And how did God make man at the firſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>In his owne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and likeneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And wherein did that Image or likeneſſe conſiſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly Sir I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, but you ſay you are a ſinfull man, how doe you know that you are ſo? </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:170659:103"/>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe I was conceived and borne in ſinne, and have ſinned all my life time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is ſin?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſurely Sir, ſinne is to doe contrary to the minde and will of God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> you know him better then I, therefore I pray you tell me what you thinke of him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes Sir, I have known him a great while, and have alwaies taken him to be a ſimple honeſt man, according to his knowledge; onely I muſt tell you, I have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeene him now and
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170659:103"/> then a little diſtempered with drinke, but of late he hath ſeemed to minde matters of Religion, for I have ſeene him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at a Lecture on the weeke day, and therefore I hope he is better now then he hath been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well neighbour <hi>Mathias,</hi> I am glad to heare that you begin to minde the beſt things, and to frequent the hearing of Gods Word more now then formerly; I pray you tell me what hath moved you ſo to doe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, a friend of mine, a godly religious man, whom
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170659:104"/> neither of you know was the firſt occaſion of it, for he telling me in an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loving manner, that he feared I was yet in my naturall eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thererefore lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Gods everlaſting wrath and damnation in Hell, his words did ſo worke upon me, that I asked him what he would adviſe me to doe; and he bad me be diligent in hearing and reading the Word of God, and get good Divinity Bookes, and one Booke he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to me above the reſt, called, <hi>The plaine mans path way to Heaven,</hi> and truly Sir, I hope the
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170659:104"/> reading of that Booke hath done me much good; but alas Sir, my ſins, my ſins are they that trouble me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But whether are they your ſinnes which you have formerly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or your preſent corruptions that doe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly Sir, they are both, for I am trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at my former ſinnes for feare they are not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and I am troubled at my preſent corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe I cannot overcome them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you tell me one thing truly, have you ever gone to the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170659:105"/> Lord in prayer about your ſins?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed Sir, I have of late divers times gone privately to prayer, and have beſought the Lord, that he would be pleaſed for Jeſus Chriſts ſake, to pardon my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins, and give me power to overcome my preſent corruptions, but yet alas all in vaine, for they doe ſtill remaine with me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But doe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that your former ſins are pardoned?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſurely Sir, I cannot beleeve that, ſo ſo long as my preſent cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions doe ſtill remaine unſubdued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:170659:105"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Weepe not I pray you, but conſider that you have gone a wrong way to worke, you would have your ſinnes ſubdued before they be pardoned, whereas the Lord doth firſt pardon ſinne, and then he gives power againſt ſinne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, I have thought with my ſelfe, that as when I was a childe, and had by the committing of any fault diſpleaſed my Father, he would at my intreating forgive me, upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that I did ſo no more; but if I committed the like fault againe, then he would not forgive the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170659:106"/> former, but reckon with me for them both: even ſo I did conceive the Lord would deale with me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But did not you tell me that you did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Lord to forgive you your ſins for Chriſt Jeſus ſake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And why have you asked it for Chriſts ſake?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe he hath ſuffered death for my ſinnes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And doe you no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> beleeve that Chriſt by his death hath fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the Juſtice of God for all your ſins.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:170659:106"/>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea Sir, I doe beleeve he hath.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then, doe you not beleeve that God for his ſatisfaction ſake hath forgiven your ſins.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Sir, I doe beleeve it ſo long as I doe continue obedient unto God in doing his Will, and not tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Commandments.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And can you not beleeve it any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then you doe ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then you doe not beleeve that God pardoneth your ſins for Chriſts ſake, but for your owne ſake, not for Chriſts obedience ſake, but for
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170659:107"/> your owne obedience ſake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed Sir, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what to ſay to that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Well neighbour <hi>Mathias,</hi> as you have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought the Lord to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and forgive you your ſinnes for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, doe ſo ſtill, but withall, beleeve that he hath done ſo according to your Petition; yea, and that abſolutely, and not conditionally as you have done, and anſwerably as you doe, ſo you ſhall be ſure to finde and feele your ſinnes mortified and ſubdued; doe but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that you are waſht
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170659:107"/> by the Blood of Chriſt from the guilt of ſinne, and you ſhall be ſure to finde that you are clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Blood of Chriſt from the filth of ſinne; let a man (ſaith Doctor <hi>Preſton</hi>) but beleeve the<note place="margin">On the new Cov.</note> the promiſe of pardon in the Blood of Chriſt, and the very beleeving the pardon will be able to cleanſe his heart from dead workes, for that faith which doth lay hold on Chriſt crucified (ſaith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother godly Divine) doth<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dyke</hi> on the Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. p. 292.</note> fetch a Crucifying vertue from him, whereby the body of corruption is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled and weakned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>O but Sir, I feare
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170659:108"/> I ſhall not beleeve that my ſins are pardoned, ſo long as they remaine unſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>If you will not beleeve that your ſins are pardoned till they are quite ſubdued, then will you not beleeve it whilſt you live; for ſo long as you live here you ſhall finde and feele ſome remainders of ſinfull corruptions unſubdued, though you doe beleeve, and if you doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve you ſhall not have them ſubdued at all by the ſanctifying Spirit of Chriſt. Indeed it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that after much ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving againſt your cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170659:108"/> in your owne ſtrength, you may ſee there is no ſtrength in you to ſubdue them as you would; and may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon goe unto Chriſt by Prayer, for grace and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to leave ſinne and doe better, and ſo live upon Chriſt that you may live upon your ſelfe; I ſay, you may goe unto Chriſt for power to doe your worke, that ſo you may earne your wages, and it is poſſible you may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon grow in legall righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, as the ſtony and thorny ground ſeed ſprung up, and increaſed much, and came neare unto maturity, and yet
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170659:109"/> this not be the worke of the ſanctifying Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt; wherefore I beſeech you, goe not this way to worke, doe not ſeeke to have the righteouſneſſe of ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation infuſed into you before you ſeeke to have the righteouſneſſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification imputed unto you, and ſo as much as in you lyeth, to goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to pervert the Lords owne order and method.</p>
                  <p>Doe you not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how I told my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Simon,</hi> that the Lords order and method in juſtifying and ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſinner is, Firſt, to
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170659:109"/> juſtifie him, by imputing the righteouſneſſe that is inherent in Chriſt unto him, and enabling him to apprehend it by faith, and then to ſanctifie him by infuſing of righteouſneſſe into him by his Spirit; and this is the method which the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi> proclaimes by way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, ſaying, <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſions of the remnant of his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, he retaineth not his anger for ever, becauſe he delighteth in mercy?</hi> Here is the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note place="margin">Micah. 7. 18.</note> of Juſtification, and then in the next Verſe he
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:170659:110"/> proclaimes the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Sanctification, ſaying, <hi>He will turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he will have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon us, he will ſubdue our iniquities &amp;c.</hi> And this method the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was well acquainted with, and therefore in the firſt Verſe of the 51. Pſalme, he beſeeches the Lord, <hi>According to the multitude of his mercies to blot out his tranſgreſſions;</hi> and then in the tenth ver. he ſaith, <hi>Create in me a cleane heart, O God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new a right ſpirit within me.</hi> Wherefore I beſeech you againe, and againe, to acquit your ſelfe with this way, and endeavour to goe on in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:170659:110"/>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>O Sir, that I could doe ſo, for ſurely I ſhould thinke my ſelfe a happy man if the Lord would both pardon mine iniquities, and ſubdue them; for truly Sir, I have lately had in my heart ſuch a deale of feare &amp; terrour of the direfull diſpleaſure of God, and of Death, and Hell, for want of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured that my ſinnes are pardoned, and I doe ſo hate, loath, and abhor thoſe corruptions which are ſtill in me, that I veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinke I ſhall never be quiet in my minde whilſt they and I live together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Weep not I pray you, except it be for joy,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170659:111"/> for ſurely this feare is a worke of the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus, for ordinarily after conviction, he lets into the hearts of his Elect ſuch feares as theſe; for although tis true, there may be in a meare natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man certaine naturall feares ariſing from the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation of his naturall conſcience, yet they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver affect his heart ſo as to worke a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his heart and his ſinnes, but your feares doe ſo affect your heart as that they worke a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration betwixt it and your Corruptions, and therefore without doubt they are as Arrowes ſhot
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170659:111"/> into your Conſcience by the arme of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But alas Sir, how can there be a ſeperation made betwixt my heart and my corruptions, ſeeth they ſtill remaine in me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Neighbour <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> if you doe hate, loath, and abhorre your corruptions as you ſay you doe, and would faine have them ſubdued, as you ſay you would, then beleeve it, and make no queſtion of it, there is ſuch a ſeperation made betwixt your heart and your ſinnes, as that they ſhall never ſeperate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betwixt the Lord and
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170659:112"/> your ſoule, for hatred of evill, ſaith that worthy Saint, Doctor <hi>Sibbes,</hi> is a ſure and never failing<note place="margin">Souls con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict. <hi>p. 476</hi>
                     </note> Character of a good ſoule; wherefore I beſeech you comfort your heart, though by reaſon of the weakeneſſe of your faith your ſinnes be not ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued as you deſire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But alas Sir, I feare I have no true faith at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, did not you tell me even now, that you feared the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpleaſure of God by reaſon of your ſins?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed Sir, I feare he is ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with me by reaſon of them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="195" facs="tcp:170659:112"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And doe you not beleeve that Jeſus Chriſt by his obedience hath pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified his anger for you, and ſo reconciled you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that Jeſus Chriſt hath pacified Gods anger for all that doe beleeve, and hath reconciled them unto him; but Sir, I feare that I doe not beleeve, and therefore I feare I am not reconciled unto God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But tell me one thing truly, Doe you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to beleeve on the name of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo be reconciled unto him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, I doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170659:113"/> it from the bottome of my heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I beſeech you leave off your wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and let me tell you to your comfort, that your deſire to beleeve is faith indeed, and your<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perkins</hi> Graine of Muſtard-ſeed, <hi>p. 21.</hi>
                     </note> deſire of reconciliation with God in Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation it ſelfe, for any man that is through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched for his ſinnes, and unfainedly deſires to have them pardoned, and to be reconciled unto God, God accepts as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eonciled, and hence it is that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5 6.</note> 
                     <hi>are they which hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, for they ſhall be ſatisfied,</hi>
                     <pb n="197" facs="tcp:170659:113"/> and againe ſaith he, <hi>If any</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 7. 38.</note> 
                     <hi>man thirſt let him come unto me and drinke,</hi> ſo that although as yet you want firme and lively faith, yet are you not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together void of faith, for you have the ſeed, conception, or bud of faith, the immortall ſeed is caſt into the furrowes of your heart, therefore wait but a while, uſing the good meanes to this end appointed, and you ſhall ſee the leaves, bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, and fruit will ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow after.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, how can theſe things be, for if a deſire of faith and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God be
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170659:114"/> faith and reconciliation indeed, then ſurely every man and woman have faith and reconciliation with God, for what man or woman is it that doth not deſire it? but I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>All men have not faith, 2 Theſſ.</hi> 3. 2.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that a man in<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perkins</hi> graine of Muſtard-ſeed, <hi>p. 18</hi>
                     </note> the ſtate of nature may deſire true happineſſe as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, who wiſhed to dye the death of the righteous, for indeed it is the property of nature to deſire the preſervation of it ſelfe, but alas, all ſuch deſires are but naturall deſires, whereas your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:170659:114"/> I am confident are ſupernaturall deſires.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>I but Sir, how ſhall I be ſure that my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are ſupernaturall?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>To the intent you may be ſure of it, I will ſhew you the true difference betwixt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſires and ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deſires, and therefore I pray you conſider, that if a mans minde be blinde, and his heart untouched and unhumbled, then all his deſires to beleeve and to be reconciled unto God can be no better then naturall deſires; and the reaſon is, becauſe that where the minde reveales not, the will affects not;
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170659:115"/> and if the heart be not touched with ſo much feare and ſorrow as doth looſen it from ſinne, and makes ſinne the ſowreſt, and Chriſt the ſweeteſt; and if there be not ſo much Humiliation as makes a man deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to renounce his owne righteouſneſſe and performances, and ſo to deſire to be found cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, there can be no ſupernaturall deſires of faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God in Chriſt, but if a mans minde be enlightened, and his heart touched and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled as yours is, then all
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:170659:115"/> his deſires of beleeving and reconciliation with God in Chriſt muſt needs be ſupernaturall deſires, and the reaſon is, becauſe that where the minde is truly enlightened, ſo that a man perceives his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate by reaſon of his ſins, and his heart is truly touched, caſt downe and humbled, it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawes it ſelfe from God as much as it can; and therefore if there be any ſpirituall motions where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the heart is lift up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, they are without doubt from the Spirit of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perkins</hi> graine of Muſtard-ſeed, <hi>p. 20</hi>
                     </note> God; ſo that although ſuch a heart dare not make out to Chriſt, (ſaith
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170659:116"/> Doctor <hi>Sibbs</hi>) yet is it<note place="margin">In his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to bruiſed Reed.</note> ſecretly upheld by the ſpirit of faith, ſhewing it ſelfe in hidden ſighs and groanes unto God; and ſuch perſons as theſe (ſaith Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi>) as have<note place="margin">Graine of Muſtard-ſeed, <hi>p. 38</hi>
                     </note> this weake faith, can ſay indeed, That they doe beleeve their ſins are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable, and they doe ſeriouſly in their hearts deſire that they were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, but as yet they cannot ſay they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt pardoned; and this I am confident is your condition.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="202-274" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, I feare that my minde was never yet truly enlightened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am ſo ignorant,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170659:116"/> and I feare I was never yet truly humbled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I now ſee that I have not renounced mine owne righteouſneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you tell me, was there not a time, and that not long ſince, that you did not know that which you now know neither concerning God, nor concerning your ſelfe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed Sir, I muſt needs confeſſe, that before I hearkned to the advice of that friend I told you of, and read that Booke which I mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned before, I neither knew any thing either concerning my miſerable condition by reaſon of my
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170659:117"/> ſins, nor yet of any reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by meanes of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then may you truly ſay with the man in the Goſpell, I was blinde, but now I ſee, for as ſure as Jeſus Chriſt did open his naturall eyes, ſo ſure hath he opened your ſpirituall eyes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But alas, I have ſuch a ſmall meaſure of knowledge, that I feare my minde is not truly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>For anſwer to this Objection, I will onely tell you what a godly and judicious Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſaith, and that is this, Be not diſmayed
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:170659:117"/> ſaith he, at the ſmall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rogers</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>p. 80.</hi>
                     </note> of thy knowledge ſo long as there is ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde in thee, if thy knowledge be ſound though weake, let it not diſcourage thee, and there may be ſoundneſſe of minde as well in a little knowledge as in much.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>I Sir, it is like that there may be ſo in others, but how ſhall I be ſure there is ſo in me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>It is very cleare and evident to me that your knowledge is ſound though weake, and that you have a ſound minde in that you know your ſelfe, your nature and your ſinnes, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:170659:118"/> humbled, for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound knowledge puffeth up, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 1. But your knowledge hath diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to you your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſo hath abaſed you in your owne eyes, and caſt you downe, and therefore doubtleſſe your minde is ſound.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>I but Sir, I told you that I alſo feared that I was never yet truly humbled, I pray you tell me what you ſay to that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And the reaſon why you feare it (as you ſay) is, for that you have not renounced your owne righteouſneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed Sir, that is the reaſon of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="207" facs="tcp:170659:118"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I pray you tell me truly, have you any hopes to be juſtified, or accepted in the ſight of God for your owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed Sir, I told you that I have had hopes, that if I ſinned no more, then the Lord would forgive my former ſins, and accept of me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But I doe not aske you what you have done formerly, but what you doe now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly Sir, you have this day made it ſo evident and cleare to me, that it is onely the Righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt received by faith,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:170659:119"/> that procures acceptance in the ſight of God, that I ſee it is my onely way to beleeve on his name, and as I told you I doe deſire ſo to doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Then beleeve it, you are truly humbled, which is a very good and ſure foundation, and therefore you are like to erect a good and ſure building, though it may be it may not goe on ſo faſt, nor make ſo glorious a ſhew as ſome others doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But alas Sir, I am ſo aſhamed, and troubled in my minde when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how farre other men doe out-ſtrip me, both in knowledge and other
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:170659:119"/> graces, that I know not what to doe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſurely you have no cauſe at all to be troubled at that, for it is to be feared there are ſome Profeſſors that grow up quickly, and flouriſh abundantly in a legall way, they are not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with inward heart corruptions as other poore ſoules are, they are full of parts, gifts, abilities, and duties which others want, and are very glorious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and yet for lack of an humble foundation they are but flittering fleeting motions, &amp; win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:170659:120"/> conceptions; whereas you or rather the Spirit of Chriſt in you, hath laid ſuch an humble foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that queſtionleſſe there ſhall be built upon it a gracious building, compoſed of many Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall Graces, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I pray you be not diſmayed, though you come farre ſhort of many vaine glorious high-ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Profeſſors; it is like the Lord ſees though it may be you doe not; that if you had ſuch parts, gifts, and abilities which ſome others have, and had not ſome ſinfull corruptions in you which it may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have not, that then
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:170659:120"/> you would he lifted up above that which is meet, and be kept in your ſelfe from Chriſt; therefore it is the Lords glorious wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to you, to let ſome of your ſinfull corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons remaine in you, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to open your eyes to ſee them, and to affect your heart with them, and to let you come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde others in gifts and parts, that ſo your ſoule may ſink in holy deſpaire of any helpe in your ſelfe, and reſt in nothing till it come to Chriſt Crucified, and the eternall ſweet promiſe in him; howbeit this you may be aſſured
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:170659:121"/> of, that if you be carefull to uſe the good meanes to this end appointed, you ſhall have ſuch a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of faith and all other graces of the Spirit of Chriſt, as ſhall be moſt fit for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>O bleſſed be the Lord if this be true; but I pray you Sir, what are the meanes which you would have me to uſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I meane hearing and reading the Word of God, meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, prayer, and receiving the Sacrament.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why Sir, I pray you, doe you thinke me ſit to come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="213" facs="tcp:170659:121"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed do I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely Sir, I am altogether unworthy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>And why doe you thinke your ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why becauſe of my ignorance and ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Then belike you thinke that knowledge and righteouſneſſe makes a man worthy to come to the Sacrament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes indeed Sir, I have had ſuch thoughts, and therefore when I heard you queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> were worthy to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Sacrament, I did much admire at it,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:170659:122"/> for that I know he is a man of great knowledge and godly life, but I doe much more admire that you ſhould thinke me to be worthy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed, if wee were to underſtand theſe words, worthy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, by way of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting and deſerving, then he in regard he hath more knowledge then you, and it may be is more free from ſome inward cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions then you, and doth more frequently performe religious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons then you, were more worthy then you; but as I told him not long ſince, we are not to underſtand
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:170659:122"/> words worthy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy by way of merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deſerving, but by way of fitneſſe and ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of diſpoſition to receive Chriſt, and taking them in this ſence, I ſay, that your ignorance and ſinfulneſſe have occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally through the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of GODS Spirit, wrought in you ſuch a fit and ſutable diſpoſition for the receiving of Chriſt, that I doe pronounce you worthy to be admitted to the Lords Table.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>O bleſſed be God if this be true; but Sir, I pray you what is this fit and ſutable diſpoſition which you ſay the Spirit
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:170659:123"/> of God hath by occaſion of my ignorance and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe wrought in me, or wherein doth it conſiſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>This fit and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table diſpoſition which the Spirit of God hath wrought in you, conſiſts in that ſight and ſence of your owne ignorant ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full miſerable and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe condition, as hath made you ſee your need of Jeſus Chriſt, to be made unto <hi>you of God wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 30</note> 
                     <hi>righteouſneſſe, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification and redemption.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, I pray you how can ſuch a diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be ſaid to make me worthy to be admitted to the Lords Table?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="217" facs="tcp:170659:123"/>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why even as we, when we ſee a miſerable poore hungry man, that is ſenceable of his owne miſerable and helpleſſe condition crave an Almes, with earneſt deſire and intreating, we doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he is in a fit and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table diſpoſition to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and account him worthy to have an Almes beſtowed upon him.</p>
                  <p>Even ſo when the Lord ſees a man ſo ſenſible of his owne miſerable and helpleſſe condition, that he ſees and feeles his need of Jeſus Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth earneſtly deſire him, he conceives him to be in a fit and ſutable
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:170659:124"/> diſpoſition to receive him, and ſo accounts him wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we read in the tenth Chapter of St. <hi>Matthewes</hi> Goſpell, that when our Saviour ſent forth his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples to preach the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that is to ſay, the glad tidings of Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sanctification, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, he ſaid unto them, verſe the 11, <hi>Into whatſoever City or Towne ye enter, enquire who in it is worthy, and there abide.</hi> And if we compare this verſe with <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 7, 8, 9. we ſhall perceive that they, and only they were thoſe worthy ones, which
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:170659:124"/> teſtified their ſight and ſence of their owne miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and their deſire to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt into their hearts, as their only reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by receiving his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples into their houſes, counting their <hi>feet very beautifull for preaching the Goſpell of peace, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them glad tidings of good things;</hi> theſe are thoſe <hi>poore</hi> ones whom our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Receive the Goſpell, Matth.</hi> 11. 5. and theſe are they who mourne under the ſight and ſence of their owne ſpirituall wants, unto whom he promiſeth <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, Mat.</hi> 5. 4. and theſe are they that hunger and
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:170659:125"/> thirſt for Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, whom he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to <hi>ſatiſfie, Matth.</hi> 5. 6.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, doe you not thinke that my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Simon</hi> hath this fit and ſutable diſpoſition wrought in him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I feare not, for it doth appeare to me that his owne ſpirit hath taken occaſion from his great knowledge to puffe him up, as the Apoſtles phraſe is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 1. yea, and it doth appeare to me that it hath taken oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion from his owne righteouſneſſe to move him to put confidence in himſelfe, and ſo he is
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:170659:125"/> hindered from ſeeing and feeling his owne need of Jeſus Chriſt, to be made unto him of <hi>God, wiſdome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 30</note> 
                     <hi>righteouſneſſe, ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and redemption.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, how can ſuch a diſpoſition be ſaid to make him unworthy to be admitted to the Lords Table.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, even as we when we ſee a ſtout and luſty Begger come to crave an Almes, and heare him flouriſh in his Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torique, and not <hi>ſpeake</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 23</note> 
                     <hi>with ſuplications,</hi> as the wiſe man ſaith the poore man doth, then we doe conceive he is not in a meet and ſutable diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:170659:126"/> to have an Almes beſtowed upon him, and therefore we uſe to ſay concerning ſuch a one, He is not worthy to have an Almes beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Even ſo when the Lord ſees a man proud of his knowledge, and confident of his owne righteouſneſſe and deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, and ſees not his need of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo conſequently not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him, then he lookes upon him as one who is in an unfit and unſutable diſpoſition to receive him, and therefore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts him unworthy of him; and therefore we read in the 13. Chapter of
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:170659:126"/> the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles, that when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> were in the City of <hi>Antioch, and preached the glad tidings of the Goſpell,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls them, verſe 32. It is ſaid verſ. 45. that the <hi>Jews ſpake againſt</hi> thoſe things <hi>which were ſpoken by Paul,</hi> contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and blaſpheming, whereupon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> waxed bold ſaith the Text, verſe 46. and ſaid, <hi>It was neceſſary that the Word of God ſhould firſt have been ſpoken to you, but ſeeing ye put it from you, and judge your ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of everlaſting life, loe, we turne to the Gentiles.</hi> Thus you ſee that theſe
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:170659:127"/> Jewes, who doubtleſſe were very knowing men in all points of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and alſo very holy and righteous according to the Law, yet becauſe they were proud of their owne knowledge, and put confidence in their owne righteouſneſſe, and ſaw no need of ſalvation by Chriſt, and ſo were not in a meet &amp; ſutable diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian to receive him; the Apoſtles counted them unworthy of him. So likewiſe we read in the 22. Chapter of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> Goſpell, that there were ſome that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to a feaſt, which the <hi>King made</hi> at the <hi>marriage
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:170659:127"/> of his Sonne,</hi> and it is ſaid verſe 5. That they made light of it, as if they had ſaid (taking it in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſence, as the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is) what tell you us of Chriſt, or of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Sanctification, or eternall Salvation to be had by beleeving on Chriſts name, we are <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> children, we are the people of God, we are a righteous Nation, and therefore ſure of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life already, and have no need of any ſuch offer; whereupon the King ſaid, verſe 8. <hi>The wedding is ready, but they that were bidden were not worthy;</hi> whereby you may alſo
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:170659:128"/> perceive that this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet and unſutable diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in not ſeeing a want of Chriſt, and ſo not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring him did render them unworthy of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I ſee that you are ſtill falling foule upon me, ſurely Sir, I thinke it is ſtrange that you ſhould altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage me, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incourage him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <hi>Simon,</hi> it appeareth to me that you have taken occaſion from thoſe good gifts and parts which God hath given you, to be puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed up, and incouraged in your ſelfe; and it doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> me that
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:170659:128"/> he hath taken occaſion from thoſe weakeneſſes and wants that are in him to be caſt downe, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged in himſelfe, and therefore I have concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it very needfull that you ſhould know that Chriſt accepts none for greatneſſe of parts, that you may not continue lifted up as you have been, becauſe of that which is of ſo little eſteem with him; and I alſo ſee it very needfull to let him know that Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth none for weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of parts, that he may not continue caſt downe and dejected, for want of that which Chriſt
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:170659:129"/> doth not ſo much regard; wherefore neighbour <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> I beſeech you to conſider what hath been ſaid, and take it home to your ſelfe for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and incouragement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, did not you ſay to our neighbour <hi>Alexander,</hi> that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge muſt of neceſſity goe before faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, I ſaid ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then Sir, me thinkes our neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> ſhould have a great meaſure of faith, becauſe he hath a great meaſure of knowledge; and me thinkes I ſhould have little or no faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:170659:129"/> you know I have little or no knowledge; and then me thinkes he ſhould be very fit to be admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I very unfit; for I remember you ſaid, That it is faith that ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s a man fit to receive the Sacrament aright.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>I, but you muſt know that this rule holds not touching the meaſure of knowledge onely, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be alſo true and ſound, ſo that although our neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> have never ſo great a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge, yet if it be not true and ſound as I feare it is not, then hath he no true faith, and
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:170659:130"/> therefore is he not fit to be admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and although you have but a very ſmall meaſure of knowledge, yet it being true &amp; ſound, as you know I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, then have you a true faith, and therefore are fit to be admitted to the Sacrament.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But yet Sir, me thinkes ſo ſmall a meaſure of faith, as the Lord knowes I have, if any at all, ſhould not fit a man to receive the Sacrament aright.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>O but you are to<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rogers</hi> on the Sacra. <hi>p. 48.</hi>
                     </note> conſider, that it is the kinde of faith that makes a man fit for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:170659:130"/> and not the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the truth of faith is rather required then any certaine meaſure; and thought you have not that meaſure of faith that you doe deſire, yet have you that truth of faith which Chriſt doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, doe you uſe to admit any to the Sacrament that are ſo weake as I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea indeed, for we doe conſider, that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſpark of fire is fire as well as the whole Element, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo is a ſparke of faith faith as well as the flame; and we muſt looke to faith in the ſparke as well
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:170659:131"/> as in the flame, knowing right well that although all Beleevers have not the like ſtrong faith, yet have they all the like precious faith, whereby they lay hold, and put on the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteouſneſſe of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. And we are not ignorant that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper was inſtituted and<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rogers</hi> on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, p. 107.</note> ordained to make weake Beleevers ſtrong, and not onely nor chiefly to make ſtrong Beleevers ſtronger.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I thanke the Lord I doe now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſee more concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sacrament of the Lords Supper then hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto I have done, for to
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:170659:131"/> ſay nothing of former times, when I went unto it and received it hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver head, not knowing any other reaſon why I ſhould receive it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others did ſo; and I thought I did God ſome ſervice, and that he was as it were beholden to me for doing ſo; even ſince I have known more then formerly, I have therein been much miſtaken, for I had thought that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, faith, repentance, love, and obedience had made a man worthy to receive the Sacrament, for I am ſure I have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heard ſome Miniſter Preach, or elſe read it in
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:170659:132"/> ſome Booke, that the wedding garment where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with a man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the Sacrament is to be cloathed is made up of all theſe, and that therefore it was for want of theſe that the man in the Goſpell was bound hand and foot, and caſt into utter darkneſſe, and therefore becauſe I found a want of all theſe in my ſelfe I thought I was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unworthy to come to the Sacrament, and durſt not preſume to come unto it; but now I doe perceive that it is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an hungering, and thirſting appetite after Chriſt and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:170659:132"/> ariſing from a true ſight and ſence of the want thereof, that makes a man worthy, and I hope I may truly ſay, That I doe ſee and feele a want thereof in ſome ſmall meaſure, and therefore Sir, I doe deſire to come to the Sacrament if you be pleaſed to admit me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Neighbour <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> if you read the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the 22. Chapter of the Goſpell written by Sr. <hi>Matthew,</hi> where the wedding garment is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in the Bible that containes <hi>Bezas</hi> notes in the Margent you ſhall find theſe words, The wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding garment is faith, to
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:170659:133"/> the which I doe aſſent, for though tis true, where faith is truly planted in the heart all the other doe proceed and grow from thence as fruits, yet it is faith that is eſpecially ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in the act of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Sacrament, it being as I told you, the hand that receiveth Chriſt, and the mouth that fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on Chriſt; yea, and it is by faith that this hungering and thirſting appetite is ſtirred up in the ſoule, therefore I ſaid, that your hungering and thirſting after Chriſt and his Righteouſneſſe is from faith, or rather faith it ſelfe, and ſo you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:170659:133"/> the wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I doe pronounce you to be one of thoſe gueſts which Chriſt invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to his Table; and therefore I as a meſſenger ſent from Chriſt, doe in the name of my Lord and Maſter Chriſt invite you to his Table, aſſuring you that he will bid you kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly welcome; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you faile not to be there the next time it ſhall be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and in the meane time I would intreat you to come before me and the Elders together, that you may alſo have their approbation, for I of my ſelfe have not power to admit you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="238" facs="tcp:170659:134"/>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>But Sir, it may be, though you doe think me fit to be admitted, yet it may be they will not, and then I ſhall be turned backe, and that will much trouble me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Feare not man, I dare warrant you that they will be all of my minde in that point con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then Sir, God willing I will come before you, and if they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo give their conſent, if the Lord ſpare me life and health, I will come to the Sacrament with my godly neighbours the next time it ſhall be adminiſtred, and in the meane time I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:170659:134"/> you Sir pray for me, that the Lord would be pleaſed to fit and prepare me to pertake thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, neighbour <hi>Mathias,</hi> as the LORD ſhall be pleaſed to enable me I will pray for you, and I beſeech you alſo in the meane time to pray for your ſelfe, and uſe all other meanes to informe your judgement aright concerning the nature, uſe, and end of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſo you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that fruit and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit which the Lord doth thereby tender and offer to ſuch as you are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that I am very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:170659:135"/> in theſe points, and therefore have great need to uſe all the meanes I can to be better informed, and truly for the preſent I know no better meanes then to intreat you to give me ſome further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction concerning the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>God willing you ſhall not want the beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions that I am able to give you, and therefore I pray you underſtand that the Sacrament of the LORDS Supper was by Chriſt himſelfe inſtituted and ordained for three eſpeciall ends.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 As firſt of all, to keep Beleevers in a continuall
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:170659:135"/> remembrance of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice which he once for all offered by his death upon the Croſſe, <hi>Doe this,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>of me;</hi> that is to ſay, Do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that my Body was broken and my Blood ſhed for the remiſſion of your ſinnes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Secondly, Chriſt did inſtitute and ordaine it to be <hi>a ſeale of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>of faith</hi> to ratifie and confirme the Covenant of promiſe made with all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers; for indeed that Covenant is as a laſt Will and Teſtament, and the Sacraments are as Seales ſet thereunto, whereby all
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:170659:136"/> the promiſes in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace or the Goſpell are ratified and confirmed to every faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule, that ſo they having both Chriſts hand and ſeale, their faith may be the better confirmed and ſtrengthned.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Thirdly, Chriſt did inſtitute and ordaine it to be ſpirituall nouriſhment to every hungry and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſoule; yea, and to be ſpirituall Phyſick to heale and cure every ſenſible ſick and diſeaſed ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Now theſe being the ends for which Chriſt did inſtitute and ordaine the Sacrament, I beſeech you let your comming there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:170659:136"/> be to obtaine theſe ends, and doe not you come for forme and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ſake, neither yet for your credit ſake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt your neighbours, neither yet out of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that your very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence there, and your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry performance of the outward acts is well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and acceptable to the Lord, as I feare me ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ignorant people have thought in former times; neither yet doe you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that for your ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord is ingaged to forgive you your ſinnes, and give you eternall life; neither yet doe you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that the bare out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:170659:137"/> actions and elements are able to ſanctifie you; in a word, beware of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving too highly of the outward acts and outward elements; but rather look to the inward inviſible matter and vertue of the Sacrament, which is, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that he is all in all in every action and in every element; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when you are at the Lords Table (as I hope you will be very ſhortly) and there ſee the Bread and Wine ſeparated by conſecration unto this holy uſe, and theſe bleſſed ends, then remember Chriſt, and thinke how
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:170659:137"/> he was fore-ordained and<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pemble</hi> on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, p. 8</note> fore-appointed by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from everlaſting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the accompliſhing of our redemption, by his death and blood-ſheding; and when you ſee the Bread broken and the Wine poured forth, then remember Chriſt, and thinke how he was torne and rent in his precious Body with ſtripes and wounds, and pained even to the death in his moſt holy Soule, full of the wrath of God, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by whom he was ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for your ſinnes, and plagued for your tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions: and when the
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:170659:138"/> Miniſter offereth unto you the Bread and Wine, then remember Chriſt, and thinke how he is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to you of God freely, yea and freely gives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to you if you will receive him; and when you receive the Bread and drinke the Wine, then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Chriſt that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Bread, and thinke how he himſelf hath ſaid, <hi>Ioh. 6. 5. 5. My fleſh is meat indeed, and my blood is drinke indeed;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that thereby hee gives life unto your ſoule, and will preſerve it to all eternity; in a word, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how God the Father did by this death and
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:170659:138"/> bloodſhed of his Sonne thus repreſented in the Sacrament, fully anſwer and ſatisfie his owne ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to the end he might ſet open a doore of mercy to all humble penitent hearted ſinners; yea, and doe you thereupon aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly beleeve that you have thereby tendered unto the Juſtice of God a full and perfect ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for all your ſinnes, and that therefore now it is a meet and equall thing with God (he having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and accepted this full ſatisfaction) to pardon and forgive you all your ſinnes, according to his promiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 28. yea,
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:170659:139"/> doe you beleeve, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly perſwade your heart, that for this ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſake you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled unto God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his promiſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. 21, 22. yea, doe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, and aſſuredly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your owne ſoule, that for the obedience and ſatisfaction ſake of Chriſt you are juſtified in the ſight of God, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 9. yea, and doe you then beleeve and make no doubt of it, but that for this ſatisfaction ſake of Jeſus Chriſt you ſhall be ſanctified by his Spirit according to his promiſe, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 12. and have
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:170659:139"/> your heart of ſtone taken out of your bowels, and a heart of fleſh given unto you, according as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 26. and have ſtrength and vigour to all holy performances, according to that promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 20, 21. yea, doe you beleeve and make no queſtion of it, but that for this ſatisfaction ſake of Chriſt you ſhall have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, according to Chriſts owne promiſe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. 51.</p>
                  <p>This you ſee is the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of promiſe; this is Chriſts laſt Will and Teſtament; theſe are the riches which he hath left and bequeathed to all ſuch
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:170659:140"/> as you are; this is Chriſts owne hand and deed, and by the Sacrament duly adminiſtred and rightly received he ſets too his ſeale, and ſo confirmes it fully; wherefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, when you are at the Sacrament, yea as oft as you ſhall be there preſent at any time here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, ſpeake to your faith as <hi>Deborah</hi> did to her ſelf, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. 12. and ſay, <hi>Awake, awake</hi> O my faith, and now beſtir and rouze thy ſelfe up to do thine office in receiving Chriſt now offered, <hi>in whom all theſe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cor. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</note> 
                     <hi>promiſes are Yea and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> Lift up thine eye to ſee Chriſt, reach forth
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:170659:140"/> thine hand and lay hold on him and receive him, ſet thy mouth to him and feed on him, eat and drink Chriſt by ſucking theſe breaſts of conſolation; and thus would I have you in the act of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Sacrament by Faith, to knit your heart unto Chriſt, and throw your ſelfe into his armes ſtretched out on the croſſe to imbrace you, and waſh your ſoule in his Blood that you may be cleane, and by Faith apply his Blood to your ſoule for the healing of all your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; ſay in your heart, Hath my Saviour died for my ſinnes, and
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:170659:141"/> ſhall not I die unto ſinne? ſhall I <hi>live any longer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>no, God forbid;</hi> and by this meanes ye ſhall finde your ſinnes weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the graces of Gods Spirit revived and ſtrengthned; yea, you ſhall finde the Sacrament to become a good cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to eat out your cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and as phyſicke to heale and cure you of all your infirmities; yea, you ſhall finde it to be, by meanes of the acting of your faith as a Conduit pipe, which being ſet to the Fountaine of grace Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall convey grace from that holy Fountaine Chriſt, into the
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:170659:141"/> ciſterne of your ſoule, and like a ſoveraigne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine you ſhall finde it to become beneficiall to all the parts of your ſoule, making you apt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to every good worke; and therefore I beſeech you to receive it often.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly Sir, by meanes of theſe your ſpeeches my judgement is much better informed touching the uſe and end of the Sacrament, and I am hereby much incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to approach thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; but Sir, becauſe you doe exhort me to receive it often, I would gladly know the reaſon why we muſt receive that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:170659:142"/> of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per often, ſeeing we are to receive the Sacrament of Baptiſme but once in all our lives.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The Reaſon is, becauſe the ſacrament of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rogers</hi> on the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, p. 360.</note> Baptiſme is the ſacrament of our Regeneration or new birth; and the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is the ſacrament of our ſpirituall nouriſhment and growth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed but once, becauſe we are borne but once; but we are to receive the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the LORDS Supper often, becauſe that after wee are borne wee ſtand in need to be often
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:170659:142"/> nouriſhed and fed, that ſo we may grow in grace; for indeed, growth in grace is a maine end and fruit of that Ordinance, God thereby giving to every faithfull Receiver the Body and Blood of his Sonne Chriſt, that by the Bread of his Fleſh and the Wine of his Blood he may cauſe them to grow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, this day hath beene a day of good tidings to me; and ſurely Sir, if the LORD have beene ſo mercifull unto me as you have declared, then have I cauſe to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and praiſe the name of the Lord as long as I live, for bringing me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:170659:143"/> this day to you; ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the Lord doe count me worthy to come to his Table, and to receive Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt with all his rich endowments, then may I truly ſay as I remember <hi>Hannah Samuels</hi> mother<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 8</note> ſaid in her ſong, <hi>He rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth up the poore out of the duſt, and lifteth up the beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from the dunghill, to ſet him among Princes, and to make him inherit the throne of glory.</hi> I little thought when I came hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with my neighbour <hi>Simon</hi> that I ſhould bee found to be more fit and more worthy to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lords Table then he; ſurely Sir, if you
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:170659:143"/> had not proved it ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſhould not have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſſure your ſelfe neighbour <hi>Mathias</hi> that this day the words of the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> are fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led concerning you two, where he ſaith, that <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth grace to the humble;</hi> and ſo are the words of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> where ſhe ſaith, that <hi>God filleth the hungry with good things, and the rich he hath ſent empty away.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I will now take my leave of you, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I cannot tell how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my thankfulneſſe to you for the great paines
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:170659:144"/> you have taken with me this day, the Lord in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy make it profitable to me, and recompence your paines to you an hundred fold, and I beſeech you Sir pray for me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Min. Now the very God of peace ſanctifie you whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and I pray God that your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 23, 24.</note> 
                     <hi>body be preſerved blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe unto the comming of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; faithfull is he he that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth you who alſo will doe it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord be with you, Sir. Come neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> will not you goe along with me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I pray you be
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:170659:144"/> going before, and I will come after you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then, I will alſo take my leave of you, and I thanke you for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering me to come along with you to this place, where I have, through the mercy of God, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo much good.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, but do not you now goe home and boaſt among our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours that Maſter <hi>M.</hi> hath found you fit to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſacrament, and me unfit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                  <p>No neighbour <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> I ſhall not do ſo, for I know that if it be ſo, it is the free mercy of the Lord towards mee, and
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:170659:145"/> therefore I deſire rather to ſpeake to my owne ſoule, and ſay unto it in the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 4. 7. For who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thee to differ from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and what haſt thou that thou haſt not received. Now if thou haſt received it, why doſt thou glory as if thou hadſt not received it.</hi> And ſo the Lord be with you both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Fare you well good neighbour <hi>Mathias.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>The Lord be with you, good neighbour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, I wiſh that I were fit to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, for I ſee there is much good
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:170659:145"/> to be gotten by the right receiving of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely neighbour <hi>Simon,</hi> if men did but know what good is to be obtained at the hands of the Lord by the right par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking thereof, and what hurt doth come to a man by not receiving it aright, they would not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to come thereunto, as indeed many doe, though it is to be feared hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver head, as we uſe to ſay, not knowing what they doe, but they would alſo endeavour to fit and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and therefore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell though you do deſire that you were fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it aright.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="262" facs="tcp:170659:146"/>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I doe perceive that he who is not fit to partake thereof is a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable man, whether he do receive it or not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>He is ſo indeed, for if he doe receive it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not fit, he doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by commit the greateſt ſinne that is unpardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and doth expoſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the greateſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that can befall a man, either here or hereafter, as you know I told my neighbour <hi>Alexander;</hi> and if he receive it not, then hee miſſeth and comes ſhort of all that good which you know I told our neighbour <hi>Mathias</hi> comes to a man by means
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:170659:146"/> of the right receiving thereof.</p>
                  <p>O then, what great care and paines ought men to take to fit and prepare themſelves to partake of that Ordinance? and how often ſhould they fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent it, being duly fitted and prepared? And yet, alas, for want of ſo doing, how many men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men by their abſence doe deprive themſelves of theſe great benefits?</p>
                  <p>Some there are that are neither fit nor willing to come; others there are that are willing to come, and yet not fit to come; and others there are that are fit to come, and yet
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:170659:147"/> not willing; as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance:</p>
                  <p>How many are there, who becauſe they cannot receive the Sacrament kneeling, as they have formerly done, are not willing to come? What ſaid an old ſimple igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant man in my hearing not long ſince? Rather then I will receive it ſo unreverently as they doe now a dayes, by ſitting at Table, as if they were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall with Jeſus Chriſt, I will never receive it while I live.</p>
                  <p>And are there not ſome others, who meerly out of a ſuperſtitious conceit doe deſire to come, and
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:170659:147"/> yet by reaſon of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſſe, are juſtly upon examination kept backe by the Elderſhip.</p>
                  <p>And are there not ſome, who it may be are fit to come, and yet doe not come; either becauſe they are aſhamed to come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo many men to bee examined, as they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed doe ſit upon that occaſion, or elſe are fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full leaſt they ſhould not be able to anſwer them to their content, and ſo be turned backe to their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.</p>
                  <p>And are there not alſo ſome others who it may be are fit to come, and yet either becauſe they
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:170659:148"/> ſcorne to be examined at theſe yeares, or by ſuch and ſuch a man, whom they doe conceive is infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to themſelves, they will not come.</p>
                  <p>And are there not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo who are fit to come, and yet doe not come, becauſe ſuch are admitted to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive are not fit to partake thereof?</p>
                  <p>Thus I ſay, either tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſuperſtitious igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, prophanneſſe, or through fooliſh ſhame or feare, or elſe through the ſinne of pride, many are kept from that great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit which otherwiſe
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:170659:148"/> they might receive by the right partaking of that Ordinance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true indeed, Sir, I ſee it clearly, and therefore I beſeech you tell me what courſe you would adviſe me to take to fit and prepare my ſelfe thereunto, that ſo I may come before you and the reſt to be admitted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Min.</speaker>
                  <p>Why truly neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor <hi>Simon,</hi> the beſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell that I can give you is to labour to become truly poore in ſpirit; that is to ſay, labour to ſee in your ſelfe a want of all good, as of your ſelfe, that ſo you may ſee your need or Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; and to this end
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:170659:149"/> I pray you conſider that<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Shepherds</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever. p. 145.</note> as a godly writer ſaith, Not onely ſome ſinne, but ſome good that a man thinkes he hath and reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in, without Chriſt, may as eaſily prove his ruine, becauſe a mans owne righteouſneſſe reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, doth not onely hide mens ſinnes, but ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens them in ſome ſinne, by which men periſh.</p>
                  <p>Truſting in a mans own righteouſnes, <hi>and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting iniquity</hi> being cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. 13. and therfore though you have forſaken all other ſinnes, yet if you doe ſtill with the Scribes and Phariſees and with zealous <hi>Paul,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:170659:149"/> his converſion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this ſin, you undoe your ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Caſt away therefore from you all your tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and confidence in your owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe amongſt the reſt, and with <hi>Paul</hi> after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, reckon it all but <hi>loſſe for Chriſt;</hi> yea, and<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 8, 9</note> judge it to be <hi>dung that you may win Chriſt and be found in him, not having your owne righteouſneſſe, which is of the Law, but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe which is of God by faith;</hi> for God as a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,<note place="margin">Sincere Convert. p. 108.</note> ſaith that godly wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in another place, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:170659:150"/> made a Law, will not forgive one ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Blood of Chriſt; Nay, ſaith hee further, Chriſts Blood will not do it neither, if thou doſt joyne never ſo little that thou haſt or doſt unto Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and makeſt thy ſelfe or any of thy duties co-partners in that great work of ſaving thee; Cry out therefore as that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Martyr did, None but Chriſt, None but Chriſt; yea, and as <hi>Richel</hi> cryed out, <hi>Give me children, or</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 30. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>elſe Idie;</hi> even ſo do you cry out, Give me Chriſt, or elſe I die: For as <hi>hee that hath the Sonne hath life;</hi> ſo he that <hi>hath not
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:170659:150"/> the Sonne, hath not life, 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 12. But for as much as you of your ſelfe have no power to do this, I beſeech you be earneſt with God in prayer, to make you ſee and feele your owne ſinfulneſſe and helpleſneſſe, and ſo your great need of Jeſus Chriſt, who is that <hi>mighty one up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom the Lord hath laid</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 4. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>help, Pſal. 89. 19. Neither is there ſalvation in any other, for there is no other name under Heaven given among men whereby wee muſt be ſaved:</hi> wherefore ſaith the holy Ghoſt, <hi>He</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>is able alſo to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by him, ſeeing hee
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:170659:151"/> ever liveth to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them;</hi> ſo that you may aſſure your ſelfe there is no need of any of your own righteouſneſſe or performances in the caſe of Juſtification or Salvation, and therefore I pray you come empty handed to Chriſt, who doth not require you to bring any thing at all to him to enrich him, but would have you come poore, and then will he inrich you, and ſo ſhall you be fit to be admitted to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; and then if you come in to us when we meet together, and make it appeare to us
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:170659:151"/> that your heart is ſo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified, we ſhall willingly ſet open the gate to you and let you in; and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching the LORD to worke this in you by the power of his owne Spirit, I will for this time take my leave of you, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to God, and to the word of his grace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sim.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I could wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly have tarried longer with you, but it may be your occaſions doe now call you away from mee, and therefore I will at this time take my leave of you, giving you many thanks for the great pains you have taken with me, and I beſeech you, Sir,
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:170659:152"/> pray for mee, and before long, God willing, I will make bold to come to you againe; for truly I am perſwaded I ſhall never be well till I have further conference with you, but no more at this time.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
